<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2016, 2020 OpenPOWER Foundation

  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.

-->
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0"
         xml:lang="en"
         xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_75822">
  <title>Dynamic Reconfiguration (DR) Architecture</title>

  <para>Dynamic Reconfiguration (DR) is the capability of a system to adapt to
  changes in the hardware/firmware physical or logical configuration, and to be
  able to use the new configuration, all without having to turn the platform
  power off or restart the OS. This section will define the requirements for
  systems that support DR operations.</para>

  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_51213">
    <title>DR Architecture Structure</title>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_22277" /> shows the relationship of the DR
    architecture with LoPAR and the relationship of the individual DR pieces
    with the base DR architecture. Each specific DR option (for example, PCI
    Hot Plug) will have a piece that sits on top of the base DR option. The
    base DR option is the set of requirements that will be implemented by all
    DR platforms and that will be utilized by the OS that supports any of the
    specific DR options. The specific DR options will call out the base DR
    option requirements as being required. Therefore, in the figure, any
    specific DR option is really that specific DR option piece plus the base DR
    option. The base DR option is not a stand-alone option; a platform which
    supports the base DR option without one or more of the specific DR option
    pieces that sit on top of it, has not implemented the DR architecture to a
    level that will provide any DR function to the user. Likewise, a DR entity
    will meet the requirements of at least one of the specific DR options, or
    else software is not required to support it as a DR entity. Thus, the base
    DR option is the common building block and structure upon which all other
    specific DR options are built.</para>
    <para>DR operations can be physical or logical. Currently the only physical
    DR entities are PCI Hot Plug. That is, the OS only has control over the
    physical DR operations on PCI IOAs. The current direction for hot plug of
    other DR entities is to do the physical hot plug (power up/down, control of
    service indicators, etc.) via the HMC and to bring the entity into usage by
    an OS via logical DR operations (Logical Resource DR -- LRDR). The PCI Hot
    Plug DR option can be found in
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_47470" />. The Logical Resource Dynamic
    Reconfiguration option can be found in
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_75053" />. It is expected that as time
    goes on, the base DR option may be expanded upon by addition of other DR
    options.</para>

    <figure xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_22277">
      <title>DR Architecture Structure</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/PAPR-18.gif" format="GIF"
          scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="figures/PAPR-18.gif"
          format="GIF" scalefit="1" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_32129">
    <title>Definitions Used in DR</title>

    <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
      <title>DR Definitions</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*" align="center" />
        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="70*" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Term</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry align="center">
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="middle" >
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Base Dynamic Reconfiguration (DR) option</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The base on which all of the specific DR options are built.
              Specific DR options include, for example, the PCI Hot Plug DR
              option, processor card DR option, etc. These specific DR options
              each include the requirement that all the base DR option
              requirements be met. See
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_51213" /> for more information
              about the structure of the DR architecture pieces.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Dynamic Reconfiguration (DR)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The capability of a system to adapt to changes in the
              hardware/firmware configuration with the power on and the OS
              operating, and to be able to use the new configuration. This is a
              piece of the High Availability puzzle, but only one of the
              pieces.</para>

              <para>Addition, removal, and replacement may, in general, be done
              with the power on or off on the connector into which the entity
              is being added or removed. For the PCI Hot Plug option, the power
              to the slot is turned off and the logic signals are electrically
              isolated from the connector during the plug or unplug
              operation.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Depth First</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>Refers to a method where a tree structure (for example, a
              set of PCI buses connected by PCI to PCI bridges) is traversed
              from the top to the bottom before all the siblings at any
              particular level are acted upon.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>DR Connector (DRC)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The term &#8220;DR connector&#8221; will be used here to
              define the plug-in point for the entity that is participating in
              DR. For example, a &#8216;slot&#8217; into which a PCI IOA is
              inserted is a DRC.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>DR Entity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>An entity that can participate in DR operations. That is,
              an entity that can be added or removed from the platform while
              the platform power is on and the system remains operational. See
              also the definitions of logical and physical DR entities.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>DR Operation</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The act of removing, adding or replacing a DR
              Entity.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Entity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>One or more I/O devices, IOAs, Processor cards, etc., that
              are treated as one unit.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>High Availability (HA) System</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A system that gives the customer &#8220;close&#8221; to
              continuous availability, but allows for some system down-time.
              Besides DR, other factors that need to be considered in the
              design of an HA system include system partitioning, clustering,
              redundancy, error recovery, failure prediction, Error Detection
              and Fault Isolation (EDFI), software failure detection/recovery,
              etc.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>I/O Adapter (IOA)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A device which attaches to a physical bus which is capable
              of supporting I/O (a physical IOA) or logical bus (a virtual IOA)
              and which has its own separate set of resources is referred to as
              an IOA. The term &#8220;IOA&#8221; without the usage of the
              qualifier &#8220;physical&#8221; or &#8220;virtual&#8221; will be
              used to designate a physical IOA. Virtual IOAs are defined
              further in
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569348_71217" />. Resources which must
              have the capability of being separate (from other devices)
              include: MMIO Load/Store address spaces, configuration address
              spaces, DMA address spaces, power domains, error domains,
              interrupt domains, and reset domains. Note that the hardware of
              an IOA may allow for separation of these resources but the
              platform or system implementation may limit the separation (for
              example, shared error domains). In PCI terms, an IOA may be
              defined by a unique combination of its assigned bus number and
              device number, but not including its function number; an IOA may
              be a single or multi-function device, unless otherwise specified
              by the context of the text. Examples include LAN and SCSI IOAs. A
              PCI IOA may exist as multiple device nodes in the OF device tree;
              that is, the OF may treat separate &#8220;functions&#8221; in an
              IOA as separate OF device tree nodes.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>IOA: built-in</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>An IOA that is not pluggable by the user. Sometimes called
              integrated I/O. As opposed to an IOA that may be removed as part
              of a plug-in card removal (see definition for a plug-in card,
              below).</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>I/O Bus</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A hardware interface onto which an IOA can be plugged on a
              platform. I/O buses discussed here include:</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>I/O Bus: PCI</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The term &#8220;PCI&#8221; refers to one of: conventional
              PCI, PCI-X, or PCI Express. The term &#8220;bus&#8221; in the
              case of PCI Express refers to a PCI Express link.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>I/O Bus: System Bus</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The system bus in a platform is normally used only to
              attach CPUs, memory controllers, and Host Bridges to bridge to
              I/O buses. A platform&#8217;s system bus may, in certain
              circumstances, be used to attach very high speed IOAs. DR of
              system bus-attached entities is not considered here.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>I/O Device</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>An entity that is connected to an IOA (usually through a
              cable). A SCSI-attached DASD device is an example. Some I/O
              devices and their connection points to the IOAs are designed to
              be plugged while the connection point is operational to the other
              I/O devices connected to the same IOA, and some are not. For
              example, while the SCSI bus was not initially designed to have
              devices added and removed while the SCSI bus was operational,
              different vendors have found ways to do so. For example,
              SCSI-attached DASD is pluggable and unpluggable from the SCSI bus
              in some platforms.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Live Insertion</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A DR operation where the power remains on at the DR
              connector. Live insertion entities are always powered unless the
              machine power is shut off or unless a subsystem containing those
              entities is shut off.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Logical DR entity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A DR entity which does not have to be physically plugged or
              unplugged during a DR operation on that entity. See
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_97022" /> for a list of the supported
              Logical DR types.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Logical Resource DR</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The name of the option for support of DR of logical
              entities. See
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_75053" />.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>PCI Hot Plug</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>DR for PCI plug-in cards where there is a separate power
              domain for each PCI Hot Plug slot. Platforms which do not provide
              individual control of power and isolation for each PCI slot but
              which do provide power and isolation control for groups of PCI
              slots (that is, multiple slots per power domain), do not provide
              &#8220;PCI Hot Plug,&#8221; but can support PCI DR.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Physical DR entity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A DR entity which may need to be physically plugged or
              unplugged during a DR operation on that entity. See
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_97022" /> for a list of the supported
              physical DR types.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Plug-in card</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A card which can be plugged into an I/O connector in a
              platform and which contains one or more IOAs and potentially one
              or more I/O bridges or switches.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Subsystem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>One or more I/O devices, IOAs, Processor cards, etc., that
              are treated as one unit, for purposes of
              removal/insertion.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_67883">
    <title>Architectural Limitations</title>
    <para>The DR architecture places a few limitations on the implementations.
    Current architectural limitations include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>DR operations will be user initiated at the software level before
        any physical plugging or unplugging of hardware is performed. This
        architecture will be flexible enough to add additional methods for invoking
        the process in the future, but for the initial architecture it will be
        assumed that the operation is invoked by the user via a software method
        (for example, invoking an OS DR services program). It is expected that some
        technologies which will be added in the future will allow
        plugging/unplugging without the user first informing the software (for
        example, P1394 and USB).</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Critical system resources cannot be removed via a DR operation.
        Which system resources are critical will not be defined by this
        architecture; it is expected that this determination will be made by the OS
        implementation and/or architecture. Loss of a critical resource would stop
        the system from operating.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Many of the RTAS calls will need to work properly, independent of
        what is powered-off (for example, NVRAM access must work during DR
        operations). This is partially encompassed by the last bullet. For more
        information, see
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936" />.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Any special requirements relative to redundant power supplies or
        cooling are not addressed here.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Moving of a DR entity from one location to another in a platform is
        supported through a &#8220;remove and add&#8221; methodology rather than a
        specific architecture which defines the constructs necessary to allow
        moving of pieces of the platform around.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para><emphasis  role="bold">Note:</emphasis> The current AIX implementation does a &#8220;remove and
    add&#8221; sequence even when the overall DR operation is a replacement.
    That is, first the old entity is removed, and then the new entity is
    added.</para>
  </section>
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_69828">
    <title>Dynamic Reconfiguration State Transitions</title>
    <para>
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_17600" /> shows the states and transitions
    for the dynamic reconfiguration entities (DR Entities). The transition
    between states is initiated by a program action (RTAS functions) provided
    the conditions for the transition are met.</para>
    <para>
    <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> Relative to
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_17600" />, physical DRC types are brought
    in to the &#8220;owned by the OS&#8221; states either: (1) by the Device
    Tree at boot time, or (2) by a DLPAR operation, which brings in the logical
    DRC &#8220;above&#8221; the physical DRC first, and drags the physical in
    as part of transferring from state 3 to state 4. Therefore no states appear
    in the &#8220;owned by platform&#8221; section under Hot Plug DR in the
    figure. So, for example, the DLPAR assignment of a PCI physical slot to an
    OS is done by assigning the logical SLOT DRC above the physical PCI slot,
    thus giving the following state transitions: state 1, to state 2, to state
    3, to state 4, at which time the OS sees the physical slot, sees an IOA in
    the physical slot (via
    <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> (dr-entity-sense) of the physical DRC
    returning &#8220;present&#8221;), and then proceeds with the state
    transitions of: state 5, to state 6, to state 7, to state 8. The reverse of
    this (DLPAR removal of the PCI slot) is: state 8, to state 6, to state 5,
    to state 4, to state 2, to state 1.</para>
    <para />
    <figure xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_17600">
      <title>Dynamic Reconfiguration State Transition Diagrams</title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/PAPR-19.gif" format="GIF" scalefit="1" />
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="figures/PAPR-19.gif"
          format="GIF" scalefit="1" width="100%" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Notes:</emphasis>
      <orderedlist>
         <listitem>
           <para>In State 5, if empty status is returned from the
           get-sensor-state dr-entity-sense call, then do not attempt to power-on</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
           <para>Transitions from State 8 to 6 or from State 6 to 5 may fail
           (<emphasis>set-indicator isolation-state</emphasis> isolate, and <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis>
           dr-entity-sense) if the hardware cannot be accessed to control
           these operations. In this case, the OS may ignore
           those errors if the operation is a DLPAR to remove the
           hardware. See also the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,ignore-hp-po-fails-for-dlpar&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
           property in <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_54493" />.</para>
         </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Base DR Option</title>

    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_98936">
      <title>For All DR Options - Platform Requirements</title>

      <para>This section contains the extra requirements placed on
      the platform for all of the various DR configurations.</para>
      <para>At this time, there are no provisions made in the DR architecture
      for unexpected removal of hardware or insertion of hardware into a DR
      connector. Therefore the user is expected to interact with the DR
      software prior to changing the hardware configuration. For example, it is
      expected that most systems will require a keyboard action prior to the
      hardware configuration change. Future architecture might allow for other
      possibilities. For example, a push-button switch at the DR connector may
      be provided which causes an interrupt to the OS to signal that an
      operation is about to take place on the connector<footnote xml:id="pgfId-546764">
        <para>The push-button method is one that has been mentioned as a
        possible enhancement for systems that are produced for telephone
        company applications.</para>
      </footnote>.</para>
      <para>As mentioned in
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_51213" />, the requirements in this
      section are not stand-alone requirements; the platform will also need to
      implement one or more of the specific DR options.</para>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> If the
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,configure-connector&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
              property exists in the
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>/rtas</literal></emphasis> node of the OF device tree, then the platform
              must meet all of the requirements for the Base DR option (that is, all of
              the requirements labeled &#8220;For all DR options&#8221;), and must also
              meet all the requirements for at least one of the specific DR
              options.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_22348">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The platform and
              OS must adhere to the design and usage restrictions on RTAS routines
              defined in
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25194" />, and any RTAS calls not
              specified in
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25194" /> must comply with
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25194" /> Note
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_82266" /> and
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_52602" />.</para>

              <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_25194">
                <title>RTAS Call Operation During DR Operations</title>
                <tgroup cols="5">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
                  <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
                  <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="20*" />
                  <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
                  <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
                  <thead valign="middle">
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">
                            <emphasis>RTAS Call Name</emphasis>
                          </emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">Reference to
                          <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25194"  xrefstyle="select: labelnumber" /> Note
                          Numbers</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">&#160;</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">
                            <emphasis>RTAS Call Name</emphasis>
                          </emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">Reference to
                          <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25194" xrefstyle="select: labelnumber" /> Note
                          Numbers</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="middle">
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>rtas-last-error</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry morerows='12'>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>ibm,read-pci-config</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>4</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>check-exception</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1, 2</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>ibm,write-pci-config</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>4,7</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>display-character</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>restart-rtas</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>event-scan</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1, 2</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>3, 4, 5</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>query-cpu-stopped-state</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>4</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>3, 4, 5</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>get-power-level</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>4</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>set-time-for-power-on</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>3, 4</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>set-time-of-day</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>get-time-of-day</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>start-cpu</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>4</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>7</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>stop-self</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>7</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>ibm,exti2c</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>system-reboot</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>ibm,os-term</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>nvram-store</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>nvram-fetch</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>power-off</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>1, 6</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis>ibm,power-off-ups</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry>
                      <!--entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry-->
                      <entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>&#160;</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold"><xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25194" xrefstyle="select: labelnumber" /> Notes:</emphasis>
                <!--anchor xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_35380" /-->

                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_82266">
                    <para>These RTAS calls
                    function as specified in this architecture, regardless of the power state
                    of any DR entity in the platform (providing the call is
                    implemented).</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_52602">
                    <para>These RTAS calls
                    do not cause errors nor return an error status by accessing hardware
                    which is isolated, unusable and/or powered down.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>These RTAS calls function properly when dealing with a DR
                    connector, when the parent of that DR connector is powered and
                    configured, regardless of the state of the child of the parent (for
                    set-indicator, the isolation-state and dr-indicator names, and for
                    get-sensor-state, the dr-entity-sense sensor name).</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The results of the OS issuing these RTAS calls to hardware when
                    the access to that hardware is through hardware which is isolated,
                    unusable, powered off, or incompletely configured, are
                    indeterminate.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The results of the OS changing the power or isolation state of a
                    Dynamic Reconfigure connector while there is an uncompleted
                    <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> operation in progress against
                    that connector are indeterminate.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Power domains which were defined within sub-trees which have
                    been subsequently isolated may remain un-modified by this call; their
                    state will be platform dependent.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The results of the OS issuing these RTAS calls to hardware which
                    is isolated and/or powered off are indeterminate.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> If there is Forth code associated
              with a DR entity, it must not modify the OF device tree properties or
              methods unless modifications can be hidden by the
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call (that is, where
              this RTAS routine recognizes the entity and creates the appropriate OF
              device tree characteristics that would have been created by the Forth
              code).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The hardware must protect against
              any physical damage to components if the DR entity is removed or inserted
              while power is on at the DR connector.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-5.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> During a DR operation (including
              resetting and removing the reset from the entity, powering up and
              powering down the entity, unisolating and isolating the entity, and
              physically inserting and removing the entity), the platform must prevent
              the introduction of unrecoverable errors on the bus or interconnect into
              which the DR entity is being inserted or removed.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-6.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> During a DR operation (including
              resetting and removing the reset from the entity, powering up and
              powering down the entity, unisolating and isolating the entity, and
              physically inserting and removing the entity), the platform must prevent
              damage to the DR entity and the planar due to any electrical
              transitions.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_48304">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-7.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> If there are any
              live insertion DR entities in a platform and if those entities or the
              rest of the platform cannot tolerate the power being turned off to those
              entities during DR operations on other DR entities, then they must not be
              placed in the same power domain as the DR entities that will be powered
              off.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_36468">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-8.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> A separate visual
              indicator must be provided for each physical DR connector which can be
              used for insertion of a DR Entity or which contains a DR entity that can
              be removed, and the indicator must be individually controllable via the
              <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS call, and must have the capability
              to be set to the states as indicated in
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_34333" /> and
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_42695" />.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_50603">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-9.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
              If a platform provides a separate indicator to indicate the state of the power for the
              DR connector, then that LED must be turned on by the platform when the
              platform turns the power on to the DR connector and must be turned off by
              the platform when the platform turns the power off to the DR
              connector.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-10.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> If a DR entity requires power to
              be turned off prior to the physical removal of the DR entity from the
              platform, then the hardware must provide a green power indicator to
              indicate the power state of the DR entity</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-11.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The platform must provide any
              necessary power sequencing between voltages within a power domain during
              DR operations (for example, during the
              <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis> RTAS call).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-12.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> If a platform supports DR, then
              all DR entities must support the full on to off and the off to full on
              power transitions.</para>
              <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> Requirement
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_22348" /> is necessary so that the OS can
              count on the availability of certain RTAS facilities and so that the OS
              does not use other RTAS facilities when they are not available. This may
              put certain hardware restrictions on what can and cannot be shut
              down.</para>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Hardware Implementation Notes:</emphasis>
              </para>

              <itemizedlist>
                <listitem>
                  <para>Requirement
                  <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_22348" /> requires careful planning of
                  hardware design and platform structure to assure that no resources
                  critical to RTAS are put into power domains that are powered down as part
                  of a DR operation. In addition, the platform is required to provide the
                  facilities (registers and bits in registers readable by firmware, etc.)
                  so that RTAS can query the state of the hardware and determine if
                  something is powered off before actually accessing the powered-off
                  hardware.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>Requirement
                  <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_36468" /> indicates that there cannot be
                  any sharing of indicators between DR connectors.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                  <para>In some large systems (for example, systems with many racks of
                  equipment) it may not be possible or convenient to view the individual DR
                  visual indicators without opening cabinet doors, etc. In such cases, the
                  designers of such systems could consider putting a &#8220;summary&#8221;
                  visual indicator where the user could readily see it, which is basically
                  a logical &#8220;or&#8221; of the visual indicators which are out of
                  sight. For example, in a rack-based system, the drawers might have an
                  indicator on the front of the drawer that indicates if any indicators on
                  the back of the drawer are flashing. This summary indicator will not be
                  accessed by the software (that is, will be transparent to the software)
                  but it is permissible for the indicator to have firmware
                  dependencies.</para>
                </listitem>
              </itemizedlist>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_82208">
      <title>For All DR Options - OF Requirements</title>
      <para>This section describes the OF properties added for DR and any
      additional requirements placed on OF due to DR.</para>
      <para>This section defines a number of new DR properties which are
      arrays. All properties for a specific DR connector under a node are at
      the same offset into each array. Also, when the descriptive text states
      &#8220;the first connector&#8221; this does not imply any physical
      position or numbering, but rather a logical &#8220;first&#8221; connector
      beneath a particular node in the OF device tree.</para>

      <section>
        <title>General Requirements</title>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_82208"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> When the firmware passes control
                to the OS, the DR hardware must be initialized such that all of the DR
                connectors which would return &#8220;DR entity present&#8221; to a
                <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> dr-entity-sense) are fully powered
                and operational and any DR visual indicators are set to the appropriate
                state (on or off) as indicated by
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_42695" />.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_82208"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> After the firmware has passed
                control to the OS, the state of the DR visual indicators must not change
                except under the following conditions:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>As directed to do so by the
                    <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS call.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Under the condition of a power-fault, in which case the hardware
                    may change the state of the visual indicator to the &#8220;off&#8221;
                    state if it turns the power off to the slot.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_82208"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The platforms which have
                hierarchical power domains must provide the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;power-domains-tree&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property in the OF
                device tree.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_17435">
        <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property</title>
        <para>This property is added for the DR option to specify for each DR
        connector an index to be passed between the OS and RTAS to identify the
        DR connector to be operated upon. This property is in the parent node of
        the DR connector to which the property applies. See
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_13582" /> for the definition of this
        property.  See <xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property" /> for additional information.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_17435"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> For each OF device tree node
                which supports DR operations on its children, the OF must provide an
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property for that
                node.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_31379">
        <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,my-drc-index&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property</title>
        <para>This property is added for the DR option to specify for each node
        which has a DR connector between it and its parent, the value of the
        entry in the
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property for that
        connector. This property is used for correlation purposes. See
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_13582" /> for the definition of this
        property.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_31379"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> For each OF device tree node
                which has a DR connector between it and its parent, the OF must provide an
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,my-drc-index&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property for that
                node.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_22748">
        <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property</title>
        <para>This property is added for the DR option to specify for each DR
        connector a user-readable location code for the connector. See
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_13582" /> for the definition of this
        property.  See <xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property" /> for additional information.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_22748"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> For each OF device tree node
                which supports DR operations on its children, the OF must provide an
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property for that
                node.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_22748"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The content of the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property must be of the
                format defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_62318" />.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_62318">
          <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property Format</title>
          <?dbhtml table-width="80%" ?><?dbfo table-width="80%" ?>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*" align="center" />
            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="70*" align="center" />
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">DRC Type</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">DRC Name</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="middle">
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>1-8, 11-30 (PCI Hot Plug)</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Location code</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>SLOT</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Location code (built-in has port suffix)</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>PORT</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Port x</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>CPU</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>CPU x</para>
                  <para>where &#8220;x&#8221; is a decimal number with one or
                  more digits and no leading zeroes</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>MEM or MEM-n</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>LMB x</para>
                  <para>where &#8220;x&#8221; is a decimal number with one or
                  more digits and no leading zeroes</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>PHB</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>PHB x</para>
                  <para>where &#8220;x&#8221; is a decimal number with one or
                  more digits and no leading zeroes</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>COPLATFAC</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>location code</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>COPLATFUN</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>location code</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_86369">
        <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property</title>
        <para>This property is added for the DR option to specify for each DR
        connector the power domain in which the connector resides. See
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_13582" /> for the definition of this
        property.  See <xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property" /> for additional information.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_45966">
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_86369"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
                For each OF device tree node which supports DR operations on its children, the OF
                must provide an
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property for that
                node.</para>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Software Implementation Notes:</emphasis>

                  <itemizedlist>
                    <listitem>
                      <para>Software will not call the
                      <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis> RTAS call with an invalid power
                      domain number, and for purposes of this call, a power domain number of -1
                      (a live insert connector) is considered invalid.</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>For the case where the power domain is -1 (the live insert case),
                      this does not imply that the connector does not need isolating before the
                      DR operation, only that it does not need to be powered off.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </itemizedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_27002">
        <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property</title>
        <para>This property is added for the DR option to specify for each DR
        connector a user-readable connector type for the connector. See
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_13582" /> for the definition of this
        property.  See <xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property" /> for additional information.</para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> The logical connectors (CPU, MEM
        etc.) represent DR boundaries that may not have physical DR connectors
        associated with them. If a physical DR boundaries were present they would
        be represented by a different DR connector type. It is possible that a
        given boundary may be represented by both a physical and a logical
        connector. In that case, logical assignment would be managed with the
        logical connector and physical add/remove would be managed by specifying
        the physical DR connector.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_27002"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> For each OF device tree node
                which supports DR operations on its children, the OF must provide an
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property for that
                node.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_79298">
        <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,phandle&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property</title>
        <para>This property is added for the DR option to specify the phandle for
        each OF device tree node returned by ibm,configure-connector. See
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_13582" /> for the definition of this
        property.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_79298"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call will include the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,phandle&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property in each OF device
                tree node that it returns. This phandle must be unique and consistent
                with any phandle visible to an OF client program or any other information
                returned by
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis>.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property">
        <title><emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> Property</title>

        <para>This property is added to consolidate the information provided by the
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis> properties.
        When present, it replaces those properties.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>For each OF device tree node which supports DR operations on its children, OF must
                provide an <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                property for that node.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property shall only
                be present if the Operating System indicates support for this new property definition,
                otherwise, the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis> will be present.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>Following live partition migration the Operating System must be prepared to support
                either the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property or the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                set of properties. The property or properties presented will based on the capability of the target partition.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_40601">
      <title>For All DR Options - RTAS Requirements</title>
      <para>For platforms that implement DR, there is one new RTAS call and
      some changes (new requirements) placed on existing ones.</para>

      <section>
        <title>General Requirements</title>
        <para>The following are the general requirements for RTAS for all DR
        options.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_40266">
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_40601"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
                If there is Forth
                code associated with a DR entity and that Forth code would normally
                modify the OF device tree properties or methods, then if that entity is
                to be supported as a DR entity on a particular platform, the
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call on that platform
                must recognize that entity and create the appropriate OF device tree
                characteristics that would have been created by the Forth code.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </section>

      <section xml:id="sec_set_power_level">
        <title><emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis></title>
        <para>This RTAS call is defined in
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569332_45884" />. Several additional requirements are placed
        on this call when the platform implements DR along with PM.</para>
        <para>This RTAS call is used in DR to power up or power down a DR
        connector, if necessary (that is, if there is a non-zero power domain
        listed for the DR connector in the
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> or
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property). The
        input is the power domain and the output is the power level that is
        actually to be set for that domain; for purposes of DR, only two of the
        current power levels are of interest: &#8220;full on&#8221; and
        &#8220;off.&#8221;</para>
        <para>For sequencing requirements between this RTAS routine and others,
        see Requirements
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25655" /> and
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_75542" />.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_set_power_level"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> the
                <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis> RTAS call must be implemented as
                specified in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569332_45884" /> and the further requirements of this DR
                option.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_set_power_level"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The
                <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis> RTAS call must initiate the operation
                and return &#8220;busy&#8221; status for each call until the operation is
                actually complete.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_35664">
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_set_power_level"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
                If a DR operation
                involves the user inserting a DR entity, then if the firmware can
                determine that the inserted entity would cause a system disturbance, then
                the
                <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis> RTAS call must not power up the
                entity and must return an error status which is unique to that particular
                type of error, as indicated in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_91238" />.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>


        <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_91238">
          <title><emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis> Error Status for specific DR
          options</title>
          <tgroup cols="4">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="10*" align="center" />
            <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="25*" align="center" />
            <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="45*" />
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Parameter Type</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Option Name</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry align="center">
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Values</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="middle">
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Out</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Status</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>PCI Hot Plug DR option</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>-9000: Powering entity would create change of frequency
                  on the bus and would disturb the operation of other PCI IOAs on
                  the bus, therefore entity not powered up.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para><emphasis role="bold">Hardware Implementation Notes:</emphasis>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>For any DR operation, the firmware could optionally not allow
              powering up of a DR entity, if the powering up would cause a platform
              over-power condition (the firmware would have to be provided with the DR
              Entities&#8217; power requirements and the platform&#8217;s power
              capability by a method which is not architected by the DR
              architecture).</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>If PM is not implemented in the platform, then only the
              &#8220;full on&#8221; and &#8220;off&#8221; states need to be implemented
              for DR and only those two states will be used.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Software Implementation Note:</emphasis> The operation of the
        <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis> call is not complete at the time of
        the return from the call if the &#8220;busy&#8221; status is returned. If
        it is necessary to know when the operation is complete, the routine
        should be called with the same parameters until a non-busy status is
        returned.</para>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_85040">
        <title><emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis></title>
        <para>This RTAS call is defined in
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_85040" />. This RTAS call will be used
        in DR to determine if there is something connected to the DR
        connector.</para>
        <para>The
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;rtas-sensors&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,sensor-&lt;token&gt;&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
        OF properties are not applicable to DR
        sensors defined in
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_92542" />.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_85040"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> RTAS must implement the
                <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> RTAS call.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_85040"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The sensor values specified in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_92542" /> must be implemented as
                specified in that table.</para>

                <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_92542">
                  <title><emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> Defined Sensors for All DR
                  Options</title>
                  <tgroup cols="4">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="10*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="25*" />
                    <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="35*" />
                    <thead valign="middle">
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Sensor Name</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Token Value</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry align="center">
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Defined Sensor Values</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry align="center">
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="middle">
                      <row>
                        <entry morerows="4">
                          <para>dr-entity-sense</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry morerows="4">
                          <para>9003</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>DR connector empty (0)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Returned for physical DR entities if the connector is
                          available (empty) for an add operation. The DR connector must
                          be allocated to the OS to return this value, otherwise a status
                          of -3, no such sensor implemented, will be returned from the
                          <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> RTAS call.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>DR entity present (1)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Returned for logical and physical DR entities when the DR
                          connector is allocated to the OS and the DR entity is present.
                          For physical DR entities, this indicates that the DR connector
                          actually has a DR entity plugged into it. For DR connectors of
                          physical DR entities, the DR connector must be allocated to the
                          OS to return this value, otherwise a status of -3, no such
                          sensor implemented, will be returned from the
                          <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> RTAS call. For DR
                          connectors of logical DR entities, the DR connector must be
                          allocated to the OS to return this value, otherwise a sensor
                          value of 2 or 3 will be returned.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>DR entity unusable (2)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Returned for logical DR entities when the DR entity is
                          not currently available to the OS, but may possibly be made
                          available to the OS by calling
                          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> with the allocation-state
                          indicator, setting that indicator to usable.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>DR entity available for exchange (3)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Returned for logical DR entities when the DR entity is
                          available for exchange in a sparing type operation, in which
                          case the OS can claim that resource by doing a
                          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS call with
                          allocation-state set to exchange.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>DR entity available for recovery (4)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Returned for logical DR entities when the DR entity can
                          be recovered by the platform and used by the partition
                          performing a
                          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS call with
                          allocation-state set to recover.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </table>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_64410" >
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_85040"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options except the PCI Hot Plug and LRDR
                options:</emphasis>
                If the
                <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> call with the dr-entity-sense sensor
                requires the DR entity to be powered up and/or unisolated to sense the
                presence of the DR entity, then the
                <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> call must return the error code of
                -9000 or -9001, as defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_44990" />, if the DR entity is powered
                down or is isolated when the call is made.</para>

                <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_44990">
                  <title><emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> Error Status for All DR
                  Options</title>
                  <?dbhtml table-width="80%" ?><?dbfo table-width="80%" ?>
                  <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="10*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="70*" />
                    <thead>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Parameter Type</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry align="center">
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Values</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="middle">
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Out</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Status</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>-9000: Need DR entity to be powered up and unisolated
                          before RTAS call</para>
                          <para>-9001: Need DR entity to be powered up, but not
                          unisolated, before RTAS call</para>
                          <para>-9002: (see architecture note, directly below)</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> The -9002 return code should not
                be implemented. For legacy implementations if it is returned, then it
                should be treated by the caller the same as a return value of 2 (DR
                entity unusable).</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_43470">
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_85040"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
                The value used
                for the sensor-index input to the
                <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> RTAS call for the sensors in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_92542" /> must be the index for the
                connector, as passed in the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> or
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property.</para>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Hardware and Software Implementation Note:</emphasis> The status
                introduced in Requirement
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_64410" /> is not valid for
                <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> calls when trying to sense insertion
                status for PCI slots (see Requirement
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_94933" />).</para>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> DR entity available for recovery
                state is intended to allow a platform to temporary allocate to itself
                resources on a reboot and then allow the OS to subsequently recover those
                resources when no longer needed by the platform. An example of use would
                be the platform temporarily reserving some LMBs to itself during a reboot
                to store dump data, and then making the LMBs available to a OS partition
                by marking them with the state of &#8220;available for recovery&#8221;
                after the dump data has been transferred to the OS.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_61130">
        <title><emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis></title>
        <para>This RTAS call is defined as shown in
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569332_27587" />. This RTAS call is used in DR to transition
        between isolation states, allocation states, and control DR indicators.
        In some cases, a state transition fails due to various conditions,
        however, a null transition (commanding that the new state be what it
        already is) always succeeds. As a consequence, this RTAS call is used in
        all DR sequences to logically (and if necessary physically) isolate and
        unisolate the connection between a DR entity and the platform. If
        physical isolation is indeed required for the DR entity, this RTAS call
        determines the necessity for isolation, not the calling program.</para>
        <para>The
        <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> allocation-state and
        <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> isolation-state are linked. Before
        calling
        <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> with isolation-state set to unisolate,
        the DR entity being unisolated will first need to be allocated to the OS.
        If the
        <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> call would return a value of DR
        entity unusable or if it would return an error like -3 for the DR entity,
        then the
        <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> isolation-state to unisolate would fail
        for that DR entity.</para>
        <para>For sequencing requirements between this RTAS routine and others,
        see Requirements
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25655" /> and
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_75542" />.</para>
        <para>A single
        <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> operation for indicator type 9001 may
        require an extended period of time for execution. Following the
        initiation of the hardware operation, if the
        <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> call returns prior to successful
        completion of the operation, the call will return either a status code of
        -2 or 990x. A status code of -2 indicates that RTAS may be capable of
        doing useful processing immediately. A status code of 990x indicates that
        the platform requires an extended period of time, and hints at how much
        time will be required before completion status can be obtained. Neither
        the 990x nor the -2 status codes imply that the platform has initiated
        the operation, but it is expected that the 990x status would only be used
        if the operation had been initiated.</para>
        <para>The following are the requirements for the base DR option. Other DR
        options may put additional requirements on this RTAS call.</para>
        <para>
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_34333" /> indicates which DR indicators
        are used with which DR connector types.</para>
        <para>The
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;rtas-indicators&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,indicator-&lt;token&gt;&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
        OF properties are not applicable to DR
        indicators defined in
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_34333" />.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_61130"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The indicator state values
                specified in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_34333" /> must be implemented as
                specified in that table.</para>

                <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_34333">
                  <title><emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> Defined Indicators for all DR
                  Options</title>
                  <tgroup cols="5">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="15*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="10*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="15*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="10*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c5" colwidth="50*" />
                    <thead valign="middle">
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Indicator Name</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Token Value</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Defined State Values</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Default Value</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry align="center">
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Examples/Comments</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="middle">
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>isolation-state</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>9001</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Isolate (0),<?linebreak?>
                          Unisolate (1)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Unisolated</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>This indicator must be implemented for DR connectors for
                          both physical and logical DR entities. Isolate refers to the DR
                          action to logically disconnect the DR entity from the platform.
                          An isolate operation makes the DR entity available to the
                          firmware, and in the case of a physical DR entity like a PCI
                          IOA, logically disconnects the DR entity from the platform (for
                          example, from the PCI bus). Unisolate refers to the DR action
                          to logically connect the entity. Before
                          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> isolation-state to unisolate,
                          the DR entity being unisolated must first be allocated to the
                          OS. If the
                          <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> call with the
                          dr-entity-sense token would return a value of DR entity
                          unusable or if it would return an error like -3 for the DR
                          entity, then the
                          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> isolation-state to unisolate
                          must fail for that DR entity.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>dr-indicator</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>9002</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Inactive (0),<?linebreak?>
                          Active (1),<?linebreak?>
                          Identify (2)<?linebreak?>
                          Action (3)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>0 if Inactive<?linebreak?>
                          1 if Active</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>This indicator must be implemented for DR connectors for
                          physical DR entities. If the DR indicators exist for the DR
                          connector, then they are used to indicate the state of the DR
                          connector to the user. Usage of these states are as defined in
                          <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_42695" /> and
                          <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569347_31867" />.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>allocation-state</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>9003</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>unusable (0)<?linebreak?>
                          usable (1)<?linebreak?>
                          exchange (2)<?linebreak?>
                          recover (3)</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>NA</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>This indicator must be implemented for DR connectors for
                          logical DR entities. Used to allocate and deallocate entities
                          to the OS. The initial allocation state of a connector is
                          established based upon the initial allocation of resources to
                          the OS image. Subsequently, an OS may request a change of
                          allocation state by use of the
                          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> with allocation-state token.
                          If the transition to the usable state is not possible the -3
                          (no such indicator implemented) status is returned.</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </table>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_16260">
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_61130"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
                The value used for the indicator-index input to the
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS call for the indicators in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_34333" /> must be the index for the
                connector, as passed in the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> or
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_61130"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> call must return a -2 status, or
                optionally for indicator type 9001 the 990x status, for each call until
                the operation is complete; where the 990x status is defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569332_10584" />.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_61130"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> If this is a DR operation that
                involves the user inserting a DR entity, then if the firmware can
                determine that the inserted entity would cause a system disturbance, then
                the
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS call must not unisolate the entity
                and must return an error status which is unique to the particular
                error.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_61130"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-5.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> If the
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> index refers to a connector that would
                return a &#8220;DR entity unusable&#8221; status (2) to the
                <emphasis>get-sensor</emphasis> dr-entity-sense token, the
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS return code must be &#8220;No such
                indicator implemented&#8221; (-3), except in response to a successful
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> allocation state usable.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_61130"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-6.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options combined with the LPAR option:</emphasis> The
                RTAS
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> specifying unusable allocation-state of
                a DR connector must unmap the resource from the partition&#8217;s Page
                Frame Table(s) and, as appropriate, its Translation Control Entry
                tables.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_61130"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-7.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options combined with the LPAR option:</emphasis> The
                successful completion of the RTAS
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> specifying usable allocation-state of a
                DR connector must allow subsequent mapping of the resource as appropriate
                within the partition&#8217;s Page Frame Table(s) and/or its Translation
                Control Entry tables.</para>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Software Implementation Note:</emphasis> The operation of the
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> call is not complete at the time of the
                return from the call if the &#8220;busy&#8221; status is returned. If it
                is necessary to know when the operation is complete, the routine should
                be called with the same parameters until a non-busy status is
                returned.</para>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Hardware and Software Implementation Note:</emphasis> The
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state) call is used to clear
                RTAS internal tables regarding this device. The
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine will need to be
                called before using the entities below this connector, even if power was
                never removed from an entity while it was in the isolated state.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_39636">
        <title><emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS Call</title>
        <para>The RTAS function
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> is a new RTAS call introduced
        by DR and is used to configure a DR entity after it has been added by
        either an add or replace operation. It is expected that the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine will have to be
        called several times to complete the configuration of a dynamic
        reconfiguration connector, due to the time required to complete the
        entire configuration process. The work area contains the intermediate
        state that RTAS needs to retain between calls. The work area consists of
        4096 byte pages of real storage on 4096 byte boundaries which can be
        increased by one page on each call. The OS may interleave calls to
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> for different dynamic
        reconfiguration connectors, however, a separate work area will be
        associated with each dynamic reconfiguration connector which is actively
        being configured. Other standard RTAS locking rules apply.</para>
        <para>The properties generated by the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> call are dependent on the
        type of DR entities. For a list of properties generated, see the RTAS
        Requirements section for each specific DR option. For example, for a list
        of properties generated for PCI Hot Plug, see
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67543" />.</para>
        <para>For sequencing requirements between this RTAS routine and others,
        see Requirement
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_25655" />.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_39636"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The RTAS function
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> must be implemented and must
                implement the argument call buffer defined by
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_50675" />.</para>

                <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_50675">
                  <title><emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> Argument Call Buffer</title>
                  <tgroup cols="3">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="15*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="15*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="70*" />
                    <thead>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Parameter Type</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Name</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry align="center">
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Values</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="middle">
                      <row>
                        <entry morerows="4">
                          <para>In</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis>Token</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Token for
                          <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis></para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis>Number Inputs</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>2</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis>Number Outputs</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>1</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis>Work area</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Address of work area</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis>Memory extent</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>0 or address of additional page</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>Out</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis>Status</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>-9003: Cannot configure - Logical DR connector unusable,
                          available for exchange, or available for recovery.</para>
                          <para>-9002: Cannot configure - DR Entity cannot be supported
                          in this connector</para>
                          <para>-9001 Cannot configure - DR Entity cannot be supported in
                          this system</para>
                          <para>-2: Call again</para>
                          <para>-1: Hardware error</para>
                          <para>0: Configuration complete</para>
                          <para>1: Next sibling</para>
                          <para>2: Next child</para>
                          <para>3: Next property</para>
                          <para>4: Previous parent</para>
                          <para>5: Need more memory</para>
                          <para>990X: Extended Delay</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </table>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_39636"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> On the first call of a dynamic
                reconfiguration sequence, the one page work area must be initialized by
                the OS as in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_44663" />.</para>

                <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_44663">
                  <title>Initial Work Area Initialization</title>
                  <?dbhtml table-width="80%" ?><?dbfo table-width="80%" ?>
                  <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
                    <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="80*" />
                    <thead>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Entry Offset</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry align="center">
                          <para>
                            <emphasis role="bold">Value</emphasis>
                          </para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </thead>
                    <tbody valign="middle">
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>0</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>entry from the
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> or
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property for
                          the connector to configure</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                      <row>
                        <entry>
                          <para>1</para>
                        </entry>
                        <entry>
                          <para>0</para>
                        </entry>
                      </row>
                    </tbody>
                  </tgroup>
                </table>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> The entry offset in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_44663" /> is either four bytes or eight
                bytes depending on whether RTAS was instantiated in 32-bit or 64-bit
                mode, respectively.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_39636"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> On all subsequent calls of the
                sequence, the work area must be returned unmodified from its state at the
                last return from RTAS.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_39636"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call must update any
                necessary RTAS configuration state based upon the configuration changes
                effected through the specified DR connector.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <para>The sequence ends when either RTAS returns a &#8220;hardware
        error&#8221; or &#8220;configuration complete&#8221; status code, at
        which time the contents of the work area are undefined. If the OS no
        longer wishes to continue configuring the connector, the OS may recycle
        the work area and never recall RTAS with that work area. Unless the
        sequence ends with Configuration Complete, the OS will assume that any
        reported devices remain unconfigured and unusable. RTAS internal data
        structures (outside of the work area) are not updated until the call
        which returns &#8220;configuration complete&#8221; status. A subsequent
        sequence of calls to
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> with the same entry from the
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> or
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property will restart
        the configuration of devices which were not completely configured.</para>
        <para>If the index from
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> or
        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis> refers to a connector
        that would return an &#8220;DR entity unusable&#8221; status (2) to the
        <emphasis>get-sensor</emphasis> RTAS call with dr-entity-sense token, the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call for that index
        immediately returns &#8220;-9003: Cannot configure - Logical DR connector
        unusable&#8221; on the first call without any configuration action taken
        on the DR connector.</para>
        <para>A dynamic reconfiguration connector may attach several sibling OF
        device tree architected devices. Each such device may be the parent of
        one or more device sub-trees. The
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine configures and
        reports the entire sub-tree of devices rooted in previously unconfigured
        architected devices found below the connector whose index is specified in
        the first entry of the work area, except those that are associated with
        an empty or unowned dynamic reconfiguration connector; where unowned
        refers to a DR connector that would return a DR entity unusable, a DR
        entity available for exchange, or a DR entity available for entity
        available for recovery value, for a
        <emphasis>get-sensor</emphasis> dr-entity-sense sensor. Configuration
        proceeds in a depth first order.</para>
        <para>If the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine returns with the
        &#8220;call again&#8221; or 990x status, configuration is proceeding but
        had to be suspended to maintain the short execution time requirement of
        RTAS routines. No results are available. The OS should call the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine passing back the
        work area unmodified at a later time to continue the configuration
        process.</para>
        <para>If the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine returns with a
        &#8220;Cannot configure - DR Entity cannot be supported in this
        connector&#8221;, then there is a lack of one or more resources at this
        connector for this DR Entity and there is at least one DR connector in
        the system into which this DR Entity can be configured. In this case, the
        DR program should indicate to the user that they need to consult the
        appropriate system documentation relative to the DR Entity that they are
        trying to insert into the system.</para>
        <para>The &#8220;need more memory&#8221; status code, is similar in
        semantics to the &#8220;call again&#8221; status. However, on the next
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> call, the OS will supply, via
        the
        <emphasis>Memory extent</emphasis> parameter, the address of another page
        of memory for RTAS to add to the work area in order for configuration to
        continue. On all other calls to
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> the contents of the
        <emphasis>Memory extent</emphasis> parameter should be 0. It is the
        responsibility of the OS to recover all work area memory after a sequence
        of
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> calls is completed.</para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Software Implementation Note:</emphasis> The OS may allocate the
        work area from contiguous virtual space and pass individual discontiguous
        real pages to
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> as needed.</para>
        <para>If the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine returns either
        the &#8220;next sibling&#8221; or &#8220;next child&#8221; status codes,
        configuration has detected an architected OF device tree device, and is
        returning its OF device tree node-name. Work Area offset 2 contains an
        offset within the first page of the work area to a NULL terminated string
        containing the node-name. Note, if the caller needs to preserve this or
        any other returned parameters between the various calls of a
        configuration sequence it will copy the value to its own area. Also, the
        first call returning configuration data will have a &#8220;next
        child&#8221; status code.</para>
        <para>The &#8220;next property&#8221; status code indicates that a
        subsequent property is being returned for the device. Work Area entry
        offset 2 contains an offset within the first page of the work area to a
        NULL terminated string containing the property name. Work Area entry
        offset 3 contains the length of the property value in bytes. Work Area
        entry offset 4 contains an offset within the first page of the work area
        to the value of the property.</para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> The
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine returns those
        applicable properties that can be determined without interpreting any
        FCode ROM which is associated with the IOA. Additionally, it is
        permissible for this RTAS call to be aware of various specific IOAs and
        emulate the action of any FCode associated with the IOA.</para>
        <para>If the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS routine returns the
        &#8220;previous parent&#8221; status code, it has come to the end of the
        string of siblings, and will back up the tree one level following its
        depth first order algorithm. The 2nd through 4th work area entries are
        undefined for this status code.</para>
        <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Software Implementation Notes:</emphasis>

          <orderedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Any attempts to configure an already configured connector or one
              in progress of being configured will produce unpredictable
              results.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The software will put the DR entity in the full on power state
              before issuing the
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call to configure the DR
              entity.</para>
            </listitem>
          </orderedlist>
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_16693">
      <title>For All DR Options - OS Requirements</title>
      <para />

      <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_83771">
        <title>Visual Indicator States</title>
        <para>DR Visual indicator usage will be as indicated in the following
        requirement, in order to provide for a consistent user interface across
        platforms. Information on implementation dependent aspects of the DR
        indicators can be found in
        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569347_31867" />.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_83771"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The visual indicators must be
                used as defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_42695" />.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

        <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_42695">
          <title>Visual Indicator Usage</title>
          <?dbhtml table-width="80%" ?><?dbfo table-width="80%" ?>
          <tgroup cols="2">
            <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
            <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="80*" />
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">State of indicator</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
                <entry align="center">
                  <para>
                    <emphasis role="bold">Usage</emphasis>
                  </para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tbody valign="middle">
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Inactive</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The DR connector is inactive and entity may be removed or
                  added without system disruption. For DR entities that require
                  power off at the connector, then the caller of
                  <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> must turn power off prior to
                  setting the indicator to this state. See also
                  <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569347_31867" />.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Identify (Locate)</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>This indicator state is used to allow the user to
                  identify the physical location of the DR connector. This state
                  may map to the same visual state (for example, blink rate) as
                  the Action state, or may map to a different state. See also
                  <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569347_31867" />.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Action</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>Used to indicate to the user the DR connector on which
                  the user is to perform the current DR operation. This state may
                  map to the same visual state (for example, blink rate) as the
                  Identify state, or may map to a different state. See also
                  <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569347_31867" />.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>
                  <para>Active</para>
                </entry>
                <entry>
                  <para>The DR connector is active and entity removal may disrupt
                  system operation. See also
                  <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569347_31867" />.</para>
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="sec_other_req">
        <title>Other Requirements</title>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_other_req"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis> The OS must detect hierarchical
                power domains (as specified in the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;power-domains-tree&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property) and must
                handle those properly during a DR operation.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_25655">
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_other_req"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
                When bringing a
                DR entity online, the OS must issue the following RTAS calls in the
                following order:</para>


                <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>If the power domain is not 0, then call
                    <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (with the isolation-state token and a
                    state value of unisolate)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_75542">
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_other_req"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all DR options:</emphasis>
                When taking a DR
                entity offline, the OS must issue the following RTAS calls in the
                following order:</para>

                <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> with the isolation-state token and a
                    state value of isolate)</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>If the power domain is not 0, then call
                    <emphasis>set-power-level</emphasis></para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_other_req"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para>When bringing a DR entity online that
                utilizes TCEs (see
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569328_76588" />), the OS must initialize the DR
                entity's TCEs.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </section>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_47470">
    <title>PCI Hot Plug DR Option</title>
    <para>This section will develop the requirements over and beyond the base
    DR option requirements, that are unique to being able to perform DR
    operations on PCI plug-in cards that do not share power domains with other
    PCI plug-in cards.</para>

    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_71112">
      <title>PCI Hot Plug DR - Platform Requirements</title>
      <para>A method will be provided to isolate the plug-in card (power and
      logic signals) and to physically remove the plug-in card from the
      machine. The physical removal may pose an interesting mechanical
      challenge, due to the position of the card edge connector relative to the
      desired direction of insertion of the card from the outside of the
      machine. In addition, PCI plug-in cards may have internal cables and may
      span multiple slots. Such mechanical issues are not addressed by this
      architecture.</para>
      <para>This section describes the requirements for the platform when a
      platform implements the PCI Hot Plug DR option.</para>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> All platform
              requirements of the base DR option architecture must be met (
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936" />).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> All PCI requirements
              must be met (for example, timing rules, power slew rates, etc.) as
              specified in the appropriate PCI specifications, and in the
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569387_87046" />.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_67003">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis>
              The hardware must
              provide two indicators per PCI Hot Plug slot, and all the following must
              be true:
              <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                <listitem>
                    <para>One indicator must be green and the platform must use the
                    indicator to indicate the power state of the PCI Hot Plug slot, turning
                    on the indicator when the slot power is turned on and turning off the
                    indicator when the slot power is turned off.</para>
                </listitem>

                <listitem>
                    <para>The other indicator must be amber and must be controllable by
                    RTAS, separately from all other indicators, and must be used as a slot
                    Identify indicator, as defined in
                    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569347_31867" />.</para>
                </listitem>
              </orderedlist>
              </para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_31404">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis>
              The hardware must
              provide a separate power domain for each PCI Hot Plug slot, controllable
              by RTAS, and that power domain must not be used by any other DR connector
              in the platform.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_94933">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-5.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis>
              The hardware must
              provide the capability to RTAS to be able to read the insertion state of
              each PCI Hot Plug slot individually and must provide the capability of
              reading this information independent of the power and isolation status of
              the plug-in card.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_17671">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-6.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis>
              The hardware must
              provide individually controllable electrical isolation (disconnect) from
              the PCI bus for each PCI Hot Plug slot, controllable by RTAS and this
              isolation when set to the isolation mode must protect against errors
              being introduced on the bus, and damage to the plug-in cards or planars
              during the plug-in card power up, power down, insertion, and
              removal.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_33017">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-7.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug option:</emphasis>
              A platform must
              prevent the change in frequency of a bus segment (for example, on the
              insertion or removal of an plug-in card) while that change of frequency
              would result in improper operation of the system.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-8.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug option:</emphasis> For each PCI Hot Plug
              slot which will accept only 32-bit (data width) plug-in cards, the
              platform must:
                <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Accommodate plug-in cards requiring up to 64 MB of PCI Memory
                    Space and 64 KB of PCI I/O space</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>For TCE-mapped DMA address space, must provide the capability to
                    map simultaneously and at all times at least 128 MB of PCI Memory space
                    for the slot.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-9.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug option:</emphasis> Each PCI Hot Plug slot
              which will accept 64-bit (data width) plug-in cards, the platform
              must:
                <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Accommodate plug-in cards requiring up to 128 MB of PCI Memory
                    Space and 64 KB of PCI I/O space</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>For TCE-mapped DMA address space, must provide the capability to
                    map simultaneously and at all times at least 256 MB of PCI Memory space
                    for the slot.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-10.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug option with PCI Express:</emphasis> The
              power and isolation controls must be implemented by use of the PCI
              Standard Hot-Plug Controller (see
              <emphasis> <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569387_87046" /> </emphasis>).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_71112"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-11.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug option with PCI Express:</emphasis> If a
              PCI Hot Plug DRC contains multiple PEs, then that DRC must be owned by
              the platform or a trusted platform agent.</para>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Hardware implementation Notes:</emphasis>

                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>Surge current protection on the planar is one way to provide the
                    required protection against damage to components if an entity is removed
                    from or inserted into a connector with the power still applied to the
                    connector.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Removal of an entity without the proper quiescing operation may
                    result in a system crash.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>In order for hot plugging of PCI plug-in cards with the system
                    operational to be useful, a mechanical means is needed in order to be
                    able to remove or insert PCI plug-in cards without shutting off system
                    power and without removing the covers above the plug-in cards (which in
                    general, would require powering-down the system).</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>It is recommended that the control of the indicators required by
                    Requirement
                    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67003" /> be via the PCI Standard Hot
                    Plug Controller (see
                    <emphasis> <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569387_87046" /> </emphasis>).</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_72553">
      <title>PCI Hot Plug DR - Boot Time Firmware Requirements</title>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_72553"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> All OF requirements
              of the base DR option architecture must be met (
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_82208" />).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_72553"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> The OF must only
              generate the
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;clock-frequency&#8221;</literal></emphasis> OF property for PCI
              bridge nodes which cannot change bus clock frequency during a PCI Hot
              Plug operation.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_72553"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> The OF must set the
              PCI configuration register bits and fields appropriately.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

      <para>
      <emphasis role="bold">Hardware Implementation Note:</emphasis> The OF should leave
      sufficient gaps in the bus numbers when configuring bridges and switches
      such that plug-in cards with bridges and switches which are to be
      supported by the platform&#8217;s DR operations can be plugged into every
      slot in the platform in which those plug-in cards are supported. That is,
      insertion of an plug-in card that contains a bridge or switch into a
      platform, requires that there be sufficient available bus numbers
      allocated to that PCI bus such that new bus numbers can be assigned to
      the buses generated by the bridges and switches on the plug-in
      cards.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_67543">
      <title>PCI Hot Plug DR - Run Time Firmware Requirements</title>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67543"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> All RTAS requirements
              of the base DR option architecture must be met (
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_40601" />).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67543"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> The
              <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS call with a indicator type of
              isolation-state and a state value of unisolate (1) must not return a
              &#8220;success&#8221; status until any IOA on a plug-in card inserted
              into the PCI slot is ready to accept configuration cycles, and must
              return a &#8220;success&#8221; status if the PCI slot is empty.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67543"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> The
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call must initialize the
              PCI configuration registers and platform to the same values as at boot
              time.</para>
              <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> During a DR replace operation, the
              replacement PCI IOA may not get placed back at the same addresses, etc.,
              as the original DR entity by the firmware (although it has to be placed
              back into the same DR connector, or it is not a DR replace operation). On
              a replace operation, the configuration information cannot reliably be
              read from the IOA being replaced (the IOA might be broken), so the
              firmware cannot read the configuration information from the old IOA and
              replace the configuration information into the new IOA.</para>
              <para>PCI I/O sub-systems architecturally consist of two classes of
              devices, bus bridges (Processor Host Bridges (PHBs), PCI to PCI Bridges,
              and PCI Express switches and bridges) and IOAs. The support that
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> provides for these two
              classes is different.</para>
              <para>For Bus Bridges, firmware will totally configure the bridge so that
              it can probe down the depth of the tree. For this reason, the firmware
              must include support for all bridges the platform supports. This includes
              interrupt controllers as well as miscellaneous unarchitected devices that
              do not appear in the OF device tree. The properties supported and
              reported are the same as provided by the boot time firmware.</para>
              <para>For PCI plug-in cards, the support is significantly less; it is
              essentially the functionality specified in section 2.5 FCode Evaluation
              Semantics of the
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569387_22451" />. However, the configuration
              proceeds as if all devices do not have an expansion ROM since the RTAS
              code does not attempt to determine if an FCode ROM is present nor
              attempts to execute it. This may, in some cases, generate different
              device node properties, values and methods than would happen had the IOA
              been configured during boot. If the IOA&#8217;s device driver or
              configuration support cannot deal with such differences, then the IOA is
              not dynamically reconfigurable. The other properties generated are
              dependent upon the IOA&#8217;s configuration header from the following
              list. If the property is not on this list the reader should assume that
              RTAS
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> will not generate it.</para>
              <para>
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_38602" /> shows what PCI OF properties
              can be expected to be returned from the
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> call for PCI Hot Plug
              operations and
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98892" /> shows some which can be
              expected to not be returned.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67543"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> The
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call when used for PCI
              IOAs must return the properties named in
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_38602" /> except as indicated in the
              Present?/Source column.</para>

              <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_38602">
                <title>PCI Property Names which will be Generated by
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis></title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*"  align="center" />
                  <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="70*" />
                  <thead>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">Property Name</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry align="center">
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">Present?/Source</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="middle">
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;name&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;vendor-id&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. From PCI header.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;device-id&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. From PCI header.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;revision-id&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. From PCI header.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;class-code&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. From PCI header.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;interrupts&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present if Interrupt Pin register not 0.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;min-grant&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Present unless Header Type is 0x01.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;max-latency&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Present unless Header Type is 0x01.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;devsel-speed&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present for conventional PCI and PCI-X.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;compatible&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. Constructed from the PCI header
                        information for the IOA or bridge.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;fast-back-to-back&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present for conventional PCI and PCI-X when Status
                        Register bit 7 is set.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;subsystem-id&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present if &#8220;Subsystem ID&#8221; register not
                        0.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;subsystem-vendor-id&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present if &#8220;Subsystem vendor ID&#8221;
                        register not 0.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;66mhz-capable&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present for conventional PCI and PCI-X when Status
                        Register bit 5 is set.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;133mhz-capable&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present for PCI-X when PCI-X Status Register bit 17
                        is set.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;266mhz-capable&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present for PCI-X when PCI-X Status Register bit 30
                        is set.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;533mhz-capable&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Only present for PCI-X when PCI-X Status Register bit 31
                        is set.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;reg&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. Specifies address requirements.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;assigned-addresses&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. Specifies address assignment.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,loc-code&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present. RTAS will have to remember the location
                        codes associated with all DR connectors so that it can build
                        this property.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,my-drc-index&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,vpd&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Always present for sub-systems and for PCI IOAs which
                        follow the PCI VPD proposed standard. See
                        <!-- FIXME: Requirement R1-12.4.2-1-->
                        <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569341_65980" /> and note to see the effect of
                        using different PCI versions.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;device_type&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>For bridges, always present with a value of
                        <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;PCI&#8221;</literal></emphasis> otherwise not
                        present.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,req#msi&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Present for all PCI Express IOA nodes which are
                        requesting MSI support, when the platform supports MSIs.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
              <para>
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98892" /> is a non-exhaustive list of
              common properties that may not be generated by RTAS
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,configure connector</literal></emphasis> for a PCI IOA. Also, the
              concept of a phandle does not apply to nodes reported by
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,configure-connector</literal></emphasis>.</para>

              <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_98892">
                <title>Non-exhaustive list of PCI properties that may not be
                generated by
                <emphasis>ibm,configure connector</emphasis></title>
                <?dbhtml table-width="80%" ?><?dbfo table-width="80%" ?>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                  <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="35*" align="center" />
                  <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="65*" />
                  <thead>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">Property Name</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry align="center">
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold">Present?/Source</emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </thead>
                  <tbody valign="middle">
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,connector-type&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- only for built-in entries not for
                        pluggable ones.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,wrap-plug-pn&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- only for built-in entries not for
                        pluggable ones.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;alternate-reg&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;fcode-rom-offset&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- RTAS does not look for this.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;wide&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;model&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;supported-network-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;address-bits&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;max-frame-size&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;local-mac-address&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;mac-address&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Never present -- needs FCode.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                    <row>
                      <entry>
                        <para>
                          <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;built-in&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                        </para>
                      </entry>
                      <entry>
                        <para>Not present for a PCI Hot Plug connectors.</para>
                      </entry>
                    </row>
                  </tbody>
                </tgroup>
              </table>
              <para>
              <emphasis>Architecture Note</emphasis>: Without
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;device_type&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and other properties, the
              OS cannot append an IOA added via DR to the boot list for use during the
              next boot.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67543"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-5.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug option:</emphasis> When
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call returns to the
              caller, if the device driver(s) for any IOA(s) configured as part of the
              call are EEH unaware (that is may produce data integrity exposures due to
              an EEH stopped state) or if they may be EEH unaware, then the
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> call must disable EEH prior
              to returning to the caller.</para>
              <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Software Implementation Note:</emphasis> To be EEH aware, a
              device driver does not need to be able to recover from an EEH stopped
              state, only recognize the all-1's condition and not use data from
              operations that may have occurred since the last all-1's checkpoint. In
              addition, the device driver under such failure circumstances needs to
              turn off interrupts (using the
              <emphasis>ibm,set-int-off</emphasis> RTAS call) in order to make sure that
              any (unserviceable) interrupts from the IOA do not affect the system.
              Note that this is the same device driver support needed to protect
              against an IOA dying or against a no-DEVSEL type error (which may or may
              not be the result of an IOA that has died). Note that if all-1&#8217;s
              data may be valid, the
              <emphasis>ibm,read-slot-reset-state2</emphasis> RTAS call should be used
              to discover the true EEH state of the device.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec_pci_hotplug">
      <title>PCI Hot Plug DR - OS Requirements</title>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_pci_hotplug"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PCI Hot Plug DR option:</emphasis> All OS requirements
              of the base DR option architecture must be met (
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_16693" />).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>

    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_75053">
    <title>Logical Resource Dynamic Reconfiguration (LRDR)</title>
    <para>The Logical Resource Dynamic Reconfiguration option allows a platform
    to make available and recover platform resources such as CPUs, Memory
    Regions, Processor Host Bridges, and I/O slots to/from its operating OS
    image(s). The Logical Resource Dynamic Reconfiguration option provides the
    means for providing capacity on demand to the running OS and provides the
    capability for the platform to make available spare parts (for example,
    CPUs) to replace failing ones (called
    <emphasis>sparing</emphasis> operations). Combined with the LPAR option,
    platforms can move resources between partitions without rebooting the
    partitions&#8217; OS images.</para>
    <para>The Logical Resource Dynamic Reconfiguration (LRDR) option deals with
    logical rather than physical resources. These logical resources are already
    physically installed (dynamic installation/removal of these resources, if
    supported, is managed via the Hardware Management Console (HMC) or Service
    Focal Point (SFP)). As such, the OS does not manage either connector power
    or DR visual indicators. Logical connector power domains are specified as
    &#8220;hot pluggable&#8221; (value -1) and DR visual indicators are not
    defined for logical connectors.</para>
    <para>The device tree contains logical resource DR connectors for the
    maximum number of resources that the platform can allocate to the specific
    OS. In some cases such as for processors and PHBs, this may be the maximum
    number of these resources that the platform supports even if there are
    fewer than that currently installed. In other cases, such as memory regions
    in a LPARed system, the number may be limited to the amount of memory that
    can be supported without resizing the cpu page frame table. The OS may use
    the
    <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> RTAS call with the dr-entity-sense
    token to determine if a given drc-index refers to a connector that is
    currently usable for DR operations. If the connector is not currently
    usable the return state is &#8220;DR entity unusable&#8221; (2). A
    <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation state) RTAS call to an
    unusable connector or (dr-indicator) to any logical resource connector
    results in a &#8220;No such indicator implemented&#8221; return
    status.</para>
    <para>Two allocation models are supported. In the first, resources are
    specifically assigned to one and only one partition at a time by the HMC.
    In this model, a DR entity state is changed from unusable to usable only by
    firmware in response to HMC requests to explicitly move the allocation of
    the resource between partitions. In the second model, certain resources may
    &#8220;float&#8221; between cooperating partitions, a partition issues a
    <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (allocation state usable) RTAS call and
    if the resource is free, the firmware assigns the resource to the
    requesting partition and returns the success status.
    <emphasis>Set-indicator</emphasis> returns the code
    &#8220;no-such-indicator&#8221; if either the resource is not free, or the
    platform is operating in the first model. To return a resource to the
    platform firmware, the OS issues a
    <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (allocation state unusable) RTAS call for
    the resource&#8217;s DR connector.</para>

    <section xml:id="sec_platform_req_lrdr">
      <title>Platform Requirements for LRDR</title>
      <para>The following requirements apply to the hardware and/or firmware as
      a result of implementing LRDR on a platform.</para>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_platform_req_lrdr"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> The hardware must provide the
              capability to power-cycle any hardware that is going to be switched
              between partitions as part of LRDR, if that hardware requires
              power-cycling to put the hardware into a known state (for example, PCI
              IOAs).</para>
              <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> Except for PCI Express IOAs that
              implement the Function Level Reset (FLR) option, since the PCI
              architecture is not specific as to the state of the IOA when the IOAs
              reset is activated and deactivated, either the platform designer will
              need to guarantee that all logic in all IOAs (including any internal
              storage associated with the IOA) is cleared to a known state by use of
              the IOAs' reset, or else the platform will need to provide the capability
              to power-cycle those IOAs, including the integrated ones (that is,
              including the non-pluggable ones). Also note that hardware which requires
              power-cycling to initialize may impact the capability to reliably reboot
              an OS, independent of whether or not LRDR is implemented.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_52827">
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_platform_req_lrdr"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis>
              Any power-cycling
              of the hardware which is done by the platform during an LRDR operation
              (for example, as part of an ibm,configure-connector operation), must be
              functionally transparent to the software, except that PCI plug-in cards
              that are plugged into a PCI Hot Plug DR connector do not need to be
              powered on before the
              <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> call for a logical SLOT DR
              connector returns to the caller.</para>
              <para>
              <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> PCI plug-in cards that are plugged
              into a DR connector will not be configured as part of an
              ibm,configure-connector operation on a logical DR connector of type SLOT
              above the plug-in card (see section 17.6.3.3 ibm,configure-connector).
              However, Requirement
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_52827" /> does require a PCI IOA which is
              not plugged in to a PCI Hot Plug DR connector (for example, soldered on
              the planar) be powered up and configured as a result of an
              ibm,configure-connector operation on a logical DR connector of type SLOT
              above such an IOA, and requires this powering up to be functionally
              transparent to the caller of ibm,configure-connector operation (a longer
              busy time is not considered to be a violation of the functional
              transparency requirement).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="sec_dr_prop">
      <title>DR Properties for Logical Resources</title>
      <para>Logical resource dynamic reconfiguration is a special case of
      general DR, therefore, certain DR properties take on special
      values.</para>
      <table frame="all" pgwide="1">
        <title>DR Property Values for Logical Resources</title>
        <tgroup cols="2">
          <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="35*" />
          <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="65*" />
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry align="center">
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Property Name</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry align="center">
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold">Property Value</emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody valign="middle">
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>As defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_17435" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,my-drc-index&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>As defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_31379" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>As defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_22748" />.<?linebreak?>
                <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis>
                This name
                allows for correlation between the OS and HMC user
                interfaces.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Logical Resource connectors are defined to be &#8220;hot
                pluggable&#8221; having a domain value of -1 per definition in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_86369" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>Shall be one of the values &#8220;CPU&#8221;,
                &#8220;MEM&#8221;, &#8220;PHB&#8221;, or &#8220;SLOT&#8221; as
                defined in
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_97022" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>
                <para>
                  <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
                </para>
              </entry>
              <entry>
                <para>As defined in
                <xref linkend="sec_ibmdrcinfo_property" />.</para>
              </entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>

      <variablelist>
       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> All platform requirements of the
              base DR option architecture must be met (
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_98936" />).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> The
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>/cpus</literal></emphasis> OF device tree node must include
              either the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
              property or the following four properties:
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis>.
              The drc-type must be type CPU, and the drc-power-domain must have the value -1. The
              property or properties must contain entries for each potentially supported dynamically reconfigurable processor.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> The root node of the OF device
              tree must include
              ither the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
              property or the following four properties:
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis>.
              The drc-type must be type MEM and the drc-power-domain must have the value -1.
              The property or properties must contain entries for each potentially supported dynamically
              reconfigurable memory region.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> The root node of the OF device
              tree must not include any drc properties (
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-*&#8221;</literal></emphasis>) for the base memory region
              (reg value 0).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-5.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> The root node of the OF device
              tree must include
              either the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
              property or the following four properties:
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis>.
              The drc-type must be type PHB, and the drc-power-domain must have the value -1.
              The property or properties must contain entries for each potentially supported dynamically
              reconfigurable PHB.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-6.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> The
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>/pci</literal></emphasis> OF device tree node representing a PHB must
              include
              either the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-info&#8221;</literal></emphasis>
              property or the following four properties:
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-indexes&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis>,
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-types&#8221;</literal></emphasis> and
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-power-domains&#8221;</literal></emphasis>.
              The drc-type must be type SLOT, and the drc-power-domain must have the value -1.
              The property or properties must contain entries for each potentially supported dynamically
              reconfigurable PCI SLOT.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-7.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> platforms must implement the
              allocation-state indicator 9003, as defined in
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_34333" />.</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>

       	<varlistentry>
          <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_dr_prop"
          xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-8.</emphasis></term>
            <listitem>
              <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> For memory LRDR, the
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,lrdr-capacity&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property must be
              included in the
              <emphasis role="bold"><literal>/rtas</literal></emphasis> node of the partition device tree (see
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569368_41461" />).</para>
            </listitem>
       	</varlistentry>
      </variablelist>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Architectural Intent -- Logical DR Sequences:</title>
      <para>This architecture is designed to support the logical DR sequences
      specified in the following sections. See also
      <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_69828" />.</para>

      <section>
        <title>Acquire Logical Resource from Resource Pool</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>The OS responds to some stimuli (command, workload manager, HMC,
            etc.) to acquire the resource, perhaps using the
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis> value as a reference if a
            human interface is involved.</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><!--anchor xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_28284" /-->The OS determines
            if the resource is usable:</para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>OS uses
                <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> (dr-entity-sense) to determine the
                state of the DR connector</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If the state is &#8220;unusable&#8221; the OS issues
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (allocation-state, usable) to attempt
                to allocate the resource. Similarly, if the state is &#8220;available for
                exchange&#8221; the OS issues
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (allocation-state, exchange) to attempt
                to allocate the resource, and if the state is &#8220;available for
                recovery&#8221; the OS issues
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (allocation-state, recover) to attempt
                to allocate the resource.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>If successful, continue, else return error status to the
                requester. If successful, this is the point where the resource is
                allocated to the OS.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Continue with DR operation.</para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The OS unisolates the resource via
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state, unisolate). This is
                the point where the OS takes ownership of the resource from the platform
                firmware and the firmware removes the resource from its resource
                pool.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The OS configures the resource using
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS.</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The OS incorporates the resource into its resource pool.</para>

                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>If the resource is a processor, the OS must use the
                    <emphasis>start-cpu</emphasis> RTAS call to move the processor from the
                    stopped state (at the end of the
                    <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis>) to the running
                    state.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The OS returns status of operation to the requester.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The OS notifies requesting entity of the OS state relative to
            the resource acquisition.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>

      <section>
        <title>Release Logical Resource</title>

        <orderedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Some entity (System administrator commanding from the HMC, a
            workload manager, etc.) requests the OS to release the resource using the
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,drc-names&#8221;</literal></emphasis> value as a
            reference.</para>

            <orderedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>The OS attempts to stop using logical resource.</para>

                <orderedlist>
                  <listitem>
                    <para>If the resource is a processor, the OS calls the
                    <emphasis>stop-self</emphasis> RTAS call then waits for the processor to
                    enter the stopped state using the RTAS
                    <emphasis>query-cpu-stopped-state</emphasis> call.</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>The OS isolates the resource via
                    <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state, isolate).</para>
                  </listitem>

                  <listitem>
                    <para>Unless the isolated resource was the partition&#8217;s last
                    processor, the OS deallocates the resource via
                    <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (allocation-state, unusable). This is
                    the point where the platform firmware takes ownership of the resource
                    from the OS. That is, the OS removes the resource from its resource pool
                    and the firmware adds it to the firmware resource pool.</para>
                  </listitem>
                </orderedlist>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>The OS returns status of operation to the requester.</para>
              </listitem>
            </orderedlist>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The OS unallocates the resource by
            <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (allocation-state, unusable).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>The system administrator may command the HMC to allocate the
            logical resource to another partition (LPAR) or reserved pool
            (COD).</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Any needed hardware removal is handled by HMC/SPC.</para>
          </listitem>
        </orderedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>RTAS Call Semantics/Restrictions</title>
      <para>This section describes the unique application of DR RTAS functions
      to the dynamic reconfiguration of logical resources.</para>

      <section>
        <title><emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state, isolate)</title>
        <para>Dynamic reconfiguration of logical resources introduces special
        meaning and restrictions to the DR connector isolation function depending
        upon the logical resource being isolated.</para>

        <section xml:id="sec_cpu_isolation">
          <title>Isolation of CPUs</title>
          <para>The isolation of a CPU, in all cases, is preceded by the
          <emphasis>stop-self</emphasis> RTAS function for all processor threads,
          and the OS insures that all the CPU&#8217;s threads are in the RTAS
          stopped state prior to isolating the CPU. Isolation of a processor that
          is not stopped produces unpredictable results. The stopping of the last
          processor thread of a LPAR partition effectively kills the partition, and
          at that point, ownership of all partition resources reverts to the
          platform firmware.</para>

          <variablelist>
           	<varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_cpu_isolation"
              xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> Prior to issuing the RTAS
                  <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> specifying isolate isolation-state of a
                  CPU DR connector type, all the CPU threads must be in the RTAS stopped
                  state.</para>
                </listitem>
           	</varlistentry>

           	<varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_cpu_isolation"
              xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> Stopping of the last processor
                  thread of a LPAR partition with the
                  <emphasis>stop-self</emphasis> RTAS function, must kill the partition,
                  with ownership of all partition resources reverting to the platform
                  firmware.</para>
                </listitem>
           	</varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sec_mem_isolation">
          <title>Isolation of MEM Regions</title>
          <para>Isolation of a MEM region creates a paradox if the MEM region being
          isolated contains the calling program (there being no program left for
          the firmware to return).</para>
          <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Note:</emphasis> The base memory region (starting at address
          zero) is not associated with a MEM DR connector. This means that the base
          memory region cannot be isolated. This restriction avoids two fatal
          conditions, attempts to isolate the region containing RTAS, and attempts
          to isolate the region containing the interrupt vectors.</para>
          <para>It is the responsibility of the OS to unmap the addresses of the
          MEM region being isolated from both PFT and the TCE tables. When the LRDR
          option is combined with the LPAR option, the hypervisor ensures that the
          addresses of the MEM region being isolated are unmapped from both the PFT
          and TCE tables before successfully completing the isolation of the MEM
          region. If any valid mappings are found, the RTAS
          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state) does not change the
          isolation-state and returns with a
          <emphasis>Status</emphasis>-9001 (Valid outstanding translation).</para>

          <variablelist>
           	<varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_mem_isolation"
              xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option:</emphasis> The caller of the RTAS
                  <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> specifying isolate isolation-state of a
                  MEM DR connector type must not be within the region being
                  isolated.</para>
                </listitem>
           	</varlistentry>

           	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_16782">
              <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_mem_isolation"
              xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option combined with the LPAR option:</emphasis>
                  The RTAS <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> specifying isolate isolation-state of a
                  MEM DR connector type must check that the region is unmapped from both
                  the partition&#8217;s Page Frame Table(s) and any Translation Control
                  Entries that would reference the memory, else the RTAS routine must
                  return with a status of
                  <emphasis>Status</emphasis>-9001 (Valid outstanding translation) and the
                  isolation-state is not changed.</para>
                </listitem>
           	</varlistentry>
          </variablelist>

          <para>
          <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Note:</emphasis> The algorithm chosen for
          implementing Requirement
          <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_16782" /> depends upon the expected
          frequency of isolation events. For RAS reasons, they should be seldom.
          For load balancing, they may be far more frequent. These methods are
          briefly described here:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>First pull the corresponding logical address from the
              partition&#8217;s valid space so setting new translations to the logical
              address are not possible. Then wait for any current in flight translation
              additions to complete. Followed by either scanning the entire PFT and TCE
              tables looking for valid translations or checking a use count for the
              particular logical address range. The PFT/TCE table search may be long,
              however, it is only done at isolation time.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>The use count method must be maintained for each add and remove
              of an address translation with the corresponding accessing of a use count
              based upon the physical real address of the memory block.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569342_11827">
          <title>Isolation of PHBs and Slots</title>
          <para>An isolation of a PHB naturally disconnects the OS image from any
          of the DR connectors downstream of the PHB (specifically any I/O slots
          and PCI Hot Plug connectors associated with the PHB). To avoid the
          complexity of gracefully managing multi-level isolation, isolation is
          restricted to only &#8220;leaf&#8221; DR connectors, that is connectors
          that have no unisolated or usable DR connectors below them. That is, for
          logical DR connectors below the connector being isolated, a
          <emphasis>get-sensor-state</emphasis> dr-entity-sense needs to return an
          unusable (2) and for physical DR connectors below the connector being
          isolated, the DR entity needs to be isolated first via
          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state, isolate). The OS is
          responsible for removing all virtual address mappings to the address
          range associated with a logical I/O SLOT before making the RTAS
          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state) call that isolates
          the SLOT. When the LRDR option is combined with the LPAR option, the
          hypervisor ensures that the addresses associated with the logical SLOT
          being isolated are unmapped from both the PFT and TCE tables before
          successfully completing the isolation of the SLOT connector. If any valid
          mappings are found, the RTAS
          <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state) does not change the
          isolation-state and returns with a
          <emphasis>Status</emphasis>-9001 (Valid outstanding translation).</para>

          <variablelist>
           	<varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_11827"
              xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a request to
                  <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state, isolate) would result
                  in the isolation of one or more other DR connectors which are currently
                  unisolated or usable, then the
                  <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS must fail with a return code of
                  &#8220;Multi-level isolation error&#8221; (-9000).</para>
                </listitem>
           	</varlistentry>

           	<varlistentry>
              <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_11827"
              xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
                <listitem>
                  <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option combined with the LPAR
                  option:</emphasis> The RTAS
                  <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> specifying isolate isolation-state of a
                  SLOT DR connector type must check that the IOA address range associated
                  with the slot is unmapped from both the partition&#8217;s Page Frame
                  Table(s) and any Translation Control Entries that would reference those
                  locations, else the RTAS routine must return with a
                  <emphasis>Status</emphasis>-9001 (Valid outstanding translation) and the
                  isolation-state is not changed.</para>
                </listitem>
           	</varlistentry>
          </variablelist>
        </section>

        <section xml:id="sec_isolation_of_coherent_platform_facilities">
          <title>Isolation of Coherent Platform Facilities</title>

          <para>Isolation of a Coherent Platform Facility (COPLATFAC) disconnects the OS
            image from any of the DR connectors downstream (Coherent Platform Functions or
            COPLATFUN) of the Coherent Platform Facility. To avoid the complex- ity of
            gracefully managing multi-level isolation, isolation is restricted to only
            leaf DR connectors, that is connectors that have no unisolated or usable DR
            connectors below them. All COPLATFUN connectors must return unusable state (2)
            during get-sensor-state before a COPLATFAC can be isolated, this is done through
            set-indicator (isolation-state, isolate). The OS is responsible for removing all
            memory mappings and detaching all processes potentially in use by co- herent
            platform functions. If valid mappings or processes are found, the set-indicator
            does not change the isolation state and returns with a Status -9001 (Valid
            outstanding translation).</para>

            <variablelist>
              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_isolation_of_coherent_platform_facilities"
                xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a
                    request to <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (isolation-state, isolate)
                    would result in the isolation of one or more other DR connectors
                    which are currently unisolated or usable, then the
                    <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> RTAS must fail with a return code of
                    Multi-level isolation error (-9000).</para>
                  </listitem>
              </varlistentry>

              <varlistentry>
                <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_isolation_of_coherent_platform_facilities"
                xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
                  <listitem>
                    <para><emphasis role="bold">For the LRDR option combined with the LPAR
                    option:</emphasis> The RTAS <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> specifying
                    isolate isolation-state of a COPLATFUN DR connector type must check that
                    all processes associated with the function are detached, else the RTAS
                    routine must return with a Status -9001 (Valid outstanding translation)
                    and the isolation-state is not changed.</para>
                  </listitem>
              </varlistentry>
            </variablelist>

        </section>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="sec_set_indicator">
        <title><emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> (dr-indicator)</title>
        <para>Logical connectors do not have associated dr-indicators (token
        value 9002). An attempt to set the state of such an indicator results in
        a &#8220;No such indicator implemented&#8221; return status.
        </para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_set_indicator"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> The calling of
                <emphasis>set-indicator</emphasis> with a token value of 9002
                (dr-indicator) and an index representing a logical connector must fail
                with a return code of &#8220;No such indicator implemented&#8221;
                (-3).</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>
      </section>

      <section xml:id="sec_ibm_configure_connnector">
        <title><emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis></title>
        <para>The
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call is used to return
        to the OS the device tree nodes and properties associated with the newly
        un-isolated logical resources and configure them for use.</para>
        <para>The
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call used against a
        logical DR connector can encounter other logical DR connectors or
        physical DR connectors below it in the tree. If a logical connector is
        encountered below a logical connector that is being configured, the
        <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call will not configure
        the sub-tree, if it is not owned by the OS (where owned refers to a DR
        connector that would return a DR entity usable, for a
        <emphasis>get-sensor</emphasis> dr-entity-sense sensor). If a physical
        connector is encountered, then the sub-tree below the physical connector
        may or may not be configured, depending on the implementation.</para>
        <para>
        <emphasis role="bold">Architecture Note:</emphasis> The requirements of this section
        specify the minimum sub-tree contents returned for various connector
        types. Implementations may optionally return other valid previously
        reported nodes that represent the current configuration of the device
        tree. Previously reported nodes may not have any changes from their
        previously reported state. A node that was removed from the configuration
        due to a DR operation and returns due to a subsequent DR operation is not
        considered to have been previously reported. It is the caller's
        responsibility to recognize previously reported nodes.</para>

        <variablelist>
         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a request to
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> specifies a connector that is
                isolated,
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> must immediately return
                configuration complete.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If the connector index refers
                to a connector that would return a &#8220;DR entity unusable&#8221;
                status (2), &#8220;DR entity available for exchange&#8221; status (3), or
                &#8220;DR entity available for recovery&#8221; status (4) to the
                <emphasis>get-sensor</emphasis> dr-entity-sense token, the
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> RTAS call must return
                &#8220;-9003: Cannot configure - Logical DR connector unusable, available
                for exchange, or available for recovery&#8221; on the first call without
                any configuration action taken on the DR connector.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a request to
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> specifies a connector of type
                CPU,
                 the returned sub-tree must consist of the specific
                cpu-node, its children, and any referenced nodes that had not been
                previously reported (such as L2 and L3 caches etc.) all containing the
                properties as would be contained in those nodes had they been available
                at boot time.</para>
                <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Implementation Note:</emphasis> Future platforms that support
                concurrent maintenance of caches, will require that high level cache
                nodes (L2, L3 etc.) are added by
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> such that their properties
                can change as new/repaired hardware is added to the platform. Therefore,
                it is the OS's responsibility when isolating a CPU to purge any
                information it may have regarding an orphaned high level cache node. The
                OS may use the
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#8220;ibm,phandle&#8221;</literal></emphasis> property to selectively
                remove caches when a processor is removed. The platform considers any
                high level cache that is newly referenced (reference count for this
                partition goes from 0 to 1) to have been previously unreported.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a request to
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,configure-connector</literal></emphasis> specifies a connector of type
                MEM,
                 the returned sub-tree must consist of the specific
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,memory-region</literal></emphasis> node containing the properties as
                would be contained in that node had it been available at boot
                time.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-5.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a request to
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> specifies a connector of type
                PHB or SLOT, then all of the following must be true:
                  <orderedlist numeration="loweralpha">
                    <listitem>
                      <para>The returned values must represent the sub-tree for the specific
                      I/O sub-system represented by the connector, except for entities below
                      any DR connectors (logical or physical) which are below the connector
                      which is the target of the ibm,configure-connector operation (that is,
                      the ibm,configure-connector operation stops at any DR connector).</para>
                    </listitem>

                    <listitem>
                      <para>The sub-tree must consist of the specific node and its children
                      all containing the properties as would be contained in those nodes had
                      they been available at boot time, including (if they exist) built-in PCI
                      IOAs.</para>
                    </listitem>
                  </orderedlist>
                </para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-6.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a request to
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> specifies a connector of type
                SLOT,
                 the returned values must represent the sub-tree for
                the specific I/O sub-system represented by the SLOT connector, and the
                sub-tree must consist of the specific
                <emphasis role="bold"><literal>/pci</literal></emphasis> node and its children all containing the
                properties as would be contained in those nodes had they been available
                at boot time, except for the PCI IOA nodes assigned to the OS image that
                contain the same properties as they would following a PCI hot plug
                operation (see
                <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569342_67543" />).</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

         	<varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-7.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a platform implementation
                powers-up and configures physical DR entities in the sub-tree under a
                logical DR connector, then a request to
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> of the logical DR connector
                must use the return status of 990x from the
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> call, as necessary, during
                the DR entity power-up sequence(s) and must control any power-up and
                sequencing requirements, as would be done by the platform during platform
                power-up.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>

          <varlistentry>
            <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_ibm_configure_connnector"
            xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-8.</emphasis></term>
              <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">For all LRDR options:</emphasis> If a request to
                <emphasis>ibm,configure-connector</emphasis> specifies a connector of
                type CO- PLATFAC or COPLATFUN, the returned values must represent the
                sub-tree for the specific coherent plat- form sub-system represented by
                the COPLATFAC or COPLATFUN connector. All properties are updated with
                the most recent data from the coherent platform resource.</para>
              </listitem>
         	</varlistentry>
        </variablelist>

      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
