<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2016 OpenPOWER Foundation
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  
-->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="section_PAPR_goals">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  
    <title> Goals of This Specification</title>
      
      <para>The specific goals of this specification are as follows:</para>
      
      <itemizedlist>
      
	    <listitem>
          <para>To create a stable platform architecture to be used by platforms based on processors 
          defined by <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569387_99718"/>. <emphasis>Processor</emphasis> 
          implementations based on this 
          architecture include IBM POWER8&#8482; processors and their successors. </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
          <para>To create an architecture which will allow platforms to operate with previous versions 
          of the OS (&#8220;n-1&#8221; capability). </para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
          <para>To leverage existing and future industry-standard buses and interfaces.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
          <para>To provide a flexible address map. Another key attribute of this specification 
          is the relocatability of devices and subsystems within the Processor Architecture (PA) 
          address space. Subsystem address information, which defines where I/O Adapters (IOAs) 
          reside, is detected by the OF and passed to the OS in the device tree. This architecture 
          accommodates the use of multiple identical buses and IOAs in the same platform without 
          address conflicts.</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
          <para>To build upon the OF boot environment defined in 
          <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569387_45524"/>.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
          <para>To provide an architecture which can evolve as technology changes. </para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
          <para>To minimize the support cost for multiple OS versions through the definition of common 
          platform abstraction techniques. Common and compatible approaches to the abstraction of 
          hardware will reduce the burden on hardware developers who produce differentiated machines.</para>
	    </listitem>

	    <listitem>
          <para>To architect a mechanism for error handling, error reporting, and fault isolation. This 
          architecture provides for the implementation of more robust systems, if desired by the system 
          developers.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
          <para>To architect a mechanism for Dynamic Reconfiguration of the hardware.</para>
	    </listitem>
	    
	    <listitem>
          <para>To provide an architecture which allows for the logical partitioning of system resources, 
          in order to execute multiple concurrent OS instances.</para>
	    </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
          
          
</section>
