<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:lang="en">
  <title>SPLPAR Characteristics Definitions</title>
  <section>
    <title xml:id="dbdoclet.50569367_15730">SPLPAR Characteristics Definitions</title>

    <para>This chapter defines the string that is returned by the
    ibm,get-system-parameter RTAS call when the parameter token value of 20
    (SPLPAR Characteristics) is specified on the ibm,get-system-parameter RTAS
    call as per <xref linkend="LoPAR.RTAS" />.</para>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>SPLPAR Terms</title>
    <para>The LoPAR Shared Processor Logical Partition option (SPLPAR) defines
    many terms as presented in 
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569367_35778" />.</para>

    <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569367_35778">
      <title>SPLPAR Terms</title>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="20*" align="center"/>
        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="80*" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Term</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry align="center">
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Definition</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="middle">
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Bound Threads</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>For virtual processor dispatches, if the hypervisor always
              dispatches a set of virtual threads together on a physical
              processor, the threads are said to be bound. This allows an
              operating system to make scheduling decisions based on cache
              affinity and work load. A change in this characteristic takes
              effect on the next reboot of the partition.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Capacity Increment</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>This defines the delta by which the entitled capacity of a
              partition can be incremented or decremented by DLPAR/WLM. The
              capacity increment is expressed as a percentage of a physical
              processor. A change in the capacity increment takes effect on the
              next reboot of the partition.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Entitled Capacity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The desired entitled capacity set by the system
              administrator in the partition definition. The desired entitled
              capacity is expressed as a percentage of a physical processor.
              The desired entitled capacity can change without a reboot of the
              partition. The entitled capacity that the partition is currently
              using may differ from the desired entitled capacity because of
              WLM actions or failed system processors.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Memory</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The desired memory set by the system administrator in the
              partition definition. The desired memory is expressed in MB of
              storage. The desired memory can change without a reboot of the
              partition. The desired memory that the partition is currently
              using may differ from the desired memory because of WLM actions
              or because of failed system memory.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Number of Processors</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The desired number of virtual processors set by the system
              administrator in the partition definition. The desired number of
              processors can change without a reboot of the partition. The
              number of processors that the partition is currently using may
              differ from the desired number of processors because of WLM
              actions or because of failed system processors.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Variable Capacity Weight</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The desired variable capacity weight set by the system
              administrator in the partition definition. The desired variable
              capacity weight is a number between 0 and 255. The desired
              variable capacity weight can change without a reboot of the
              partition. The variable capacity weight that the partition is
              currently using may differ from the desired variable capacity
              because of WLM actions.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Dispatch Wheel Rotation Period</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The duration of the hypervisor&#8217;s scheduling window.
              The time over which the entitled capacity of a virtual processor
              has to be utilized by the partition. At the start of a dispatch
              wheel rotation period, each virtual processor is eligible for CPU
              time corresponding to its entitled capacity. If the entire
              entitled capacity of a virtual processor is not utilized during a
              dispatch wheel rotation period, the unused entitled capacity is
              lost. The dispatch wheel rotation period is expressed as N number
              of time base ticks. The dispatch wheel duration of a partition
              with a capacity increment of 100 is 0. A change in the dispatch
              wheel rotation period takes effect on the next reboot of the
              partition.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Entitled Capacity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The minimum entitled capacity that is needed to power on
              the partition. The capacity is expressed as a percentage of a
              physical processor. The minimum entitled capacity is set by the
              system administrator in the partition definition. DLPAR cannot
              take the entitled capacity below the minimum entitled capacity. A
              change in the minimum entitled capacity takes effect on the next
              reboot of the partition. A partition can give up its entitled
              capacity to be below the minimum entitled capacity.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Entitled Capacity per Virtual Processor</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The minimum entitled capacity that the platform requires
              for a virtual processor of any partition on the platform. The
              minimum virtual per virtual processor is enforced by the HMC in
              the partition definition and by the hypervisor for H_SET_PPP (
              <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569344_14689" />). A change in the
              minimum entitled capacity per virtual processor takes effect on
              the next reboot of the partition.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Memory</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The minimum amount of main store that is needed to power on
              the partition. Minimum memory is expressed in MB of storage. The
              minimum memory is set by the system administrator in the
              partition definition. DLPAR cannot take the partition memory
              below the minimum memory. A change in the minimum memory takes
              effect on the next reboot of the partition. A partition can
              always give up its memory to go below the minimum memory.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Number of Processors</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The minimum number of virtual processors that are needed to
              start the partition. The minimum number of virtual processors is
              set by the system administrator in the partition definition.
              DLPAR cannot take the number of virtual processors below the
              minimum number of processors. A change in the minimum number of
              processors takes effect on the next reboot of the partition. A
              partition can always give up its virtual processors to go below
              the minimum number of processors.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Maximum Entitled Capacity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The maximum entitled capacity currently that can be
              assigned to the partition through DLPAR/WLM. The capacity is
              expressed as a percentage of a physical processor. The Maximum
              entitled capacity is set up by the system administrator in the
              partition definition. A change in the maximum entitled capacity
              maximum takes effect on the next reboot of the partition.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Maximum Platform Processors</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>The maximum number of processors that can be active on the
              platform. A change in the maximum platform processors takes
              effect on the next reboot of the partition.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Dedicated Donate Mode</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>For a partition with a capacity increment of 100, the
              platform uses a dedicated CPU to actualize a virtual processor of
              the partition. For such a partition, the platform can increase
              the capacity of the shared processor pool by utilizing the unused
              processor capacity of the partition. If the platform supports the
              dedicated donate function, it can be enabled by the system
              administrator in the partition definition. The value of this
              characteristic can change without a reboot of the
              partition.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Thread</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>A multi threaded processor may have multiple contexts
              executing concurrently. Each of them is called a thread. From a
              software viewpoint, a thread is an independent executing unit.
              Threads on a processor share some of the architected and
              unarchitected resources of a physical processor.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Key Words And Values</title>
    <para>Table 
    <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569367_78034" /> defines the key words and the
    associated legal values that will be returned in the ASCII NULL terminated
    string when the parameter token value of 20 (SPLPAR characteristics) is
    specified on the ibm,get-system-parameter RTAS call. The key word and value
    is separated by an ascii equal (&#8220;=&#8221;). Each key word, value pair
    is delimited by an ascii comma in the string. The numerical value of the
    characteristic corresponding to the key word is the decimal number that
    corresponds to the numeric characters in the value part of the key word,
    value pair.</para>
    <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569367_78034">
      <title>SPLPAR Characteristics</title>
      <?dbhtml table-width="75%" ?><?dbfo table-width="75%" ?>
      <tgroup cols="4">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="35*" align="center" />
        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="25*" align="center" />
        <colspec colname="c3" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
        <colspec colname="c4" colwidth="20*" align="center" />
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Characteristics</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Key Word</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Values</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Notes</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="middle">
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Bound Threads</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>BoundThrds</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0,1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>1</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Capacity Increment</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>CapInc</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>1 through 100</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>&#160;</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Dispatch Wheel Rotation Period</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>DisWheRotPer</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>1 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>&#160;</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Entitled Capacity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>MinEntCap</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>2</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Entitled Capacity per Virtual Processor</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>MinEntCapPerVP</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>1 through 100</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>&#160;</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Memory</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>MinMem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>&#160;</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Minimum Number of Processors</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>MinProcs</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>&#160;</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Maximum Entitled Capacity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>MaxEntCap</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>1 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>3</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Maximum Platform Processors</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>MaxPlatProcs</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>1 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>&#160;</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Entitled Capacity</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>DesEntCap</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>4</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Memory</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>DesMem</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>5</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Number of Processors</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>DesProcs</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0 through N</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>6</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Desired Variable Capacity Weight</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>DesVarCapWt</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0 through 255</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>&#160;</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>Dedicated Donate Mode</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>DedDonMode</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>0,1</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para>7</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
    <para><emphasis  role="bold">Notes:</emphasis>
      <orderedlist>		      
        <listitem>
          <para>0=Threads are not bound, 1=Threads are bound.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The maximum numeric value of Minimum Entitled Capacity is the
          number of processors on the platform multiplied by 100.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The maximum numeric value of Maximum Entitled Capacity is the
          number of processors on the platform multiplied by 100.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The numeric value of Desired Entitled Capacity is greater or equal
          than the numeric value of the Minimum Entitled Capacity and less than or
          equal to the numeric value of the Maximum Entitled Capacity.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The numeric value of Desired Memory is greater or equal than the
          numeric value of the Minimum Memory and less than or equal to the maximum
          memory set by the system administrator in the partition profile.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>The numeric value of Desired Number of Processors is greater or
          equal than the numeric value of the Minimum Number of Processors and less
          than or equal to the maximum number of virtual processors set by the system
          administrator in the partition profile.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>0=Dedicated Donate Mode is disabled, 1=Dedicated Donate Mode is
          enabled.</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>		      
    </para>
  </section>
</chapter>
