<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_35960"
version="5.0" 
xml:lang="en">
  <title>Non Uniform Memory Access (NUMA) Option</title>
  
  <section>
    <title>Summary of Extensions to Support NUMA</title>
    <para>NUMA platforms to a first level approximation are simply a large 
    scale Symmetric Multi-Processor. However to tune system performance and to aid 
    in platform maintenance, the OS needs additional information and mechanisms. 
    These include:</para>

    <itemizedlist>		      
      <listitem>
        <para>Associativity -- to determine the platform resource 
        groupings.</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Relative Performance Distances -- to determine the performance 
        between resources within different groupings.</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Performance Monitor -- to provide usage data on the NUMA 
        fabric.</para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
        <para>Dynamic Reconfiguration -- due to such causes as platform upgrade, 
        reallocation of resources, or a repair of a failure.</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>		      

    <para>There are two NUMA support options: the &#x201C;NUMA&#x201D; option 
    and its proper subset the &#x201C;Associativity Information&#x201D; 
    option.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_90086">
    <title>NUMA Resource Associativity</title>
    <para>Associativity Codes represent the groupings of the various platform 
    resources into domains of substantially similar mean performance relative to 
    resources outside of that domain. Resources subsets of a given domain that 
    exhibit better performance relative to each other than relative to other 
    resources subsets, are represented as being members of a sub-grouping domain. 
    Such sub-domain grouping is represented to any level deemed significant by the 
    platform design. <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_57930"/> presents a simple 
    system configuration with one possible decomposition into associativity 
    domains. From the decomposition provided the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> value string for each resource is 
    enumerated. </para>

    <figure xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_57930">
      <title>Example NUMA configuration with 
      domains and corresponding <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
      values  </title>
      <mediaobject>
        <imageobject role="html">
          <imagedata fileref="figures/PAPR-32.gif" format="GIF" scalefit="1"/>
        </imageobject>
        <imageobject role="fo">
          <imagedata contentdepth="100%" fileref="figures/PAPR-32.gif" format="GIF" scalefit="1" width="100%"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject>
    </figure>
 
    <para> The OF Device Tree node for each allocable resource 
    (processor, memory region, and IO slot) conveys information about the resources 
    statically assigned to the client program; and contains the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property (see <xref linkend="LoPAR.RTAS"/>). This property allows the client 
    program to determine the associativity between any two of it&#x2019;s 
    resources. The greater the associativity the greater the expected performance 
    when using those two resources in a given operation.</para>
    <para>The legal form of the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property is dependent upon the setting of the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,architecture-vec-5&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property byte 5 bit 0. The bit value of zero allows the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property string to be sequenced in 
    priority order; this form is being deprecated for new implementations in favor 
    of the form indicated by the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,architecture-vec-5&#x201D;</literal></emphasis>
    property byte 5 bit 0 having the value of one in which the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property string represents the 
    strict physical hierarchy of the platform.</para>
    <para>When the LPAR option is also implemented, the partition virtual 
    resources may be mapped onto physical resources with in a very dynamic manor. 
    Given that the resource mapping to the associativity domain is substantially 
    consistent, the client program can make use of the associativity information to 
    on the average optimize performance. If the resource mapping to the 
    associativity domain is substantially inconsistent, then associativity 
    information for the resources is not provided to prevent erroneous operation. 
    If the long term mapping changes the client program can be made aware of the 
    new associativity information using the <emphasis>ibm,update-properties</emphasis> RTAS call (See 
    <xref linkend="LoPAR.RTAS"/>).</para>

    <variablelist>
     	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_19785">
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_90086" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the NUMA or Associativity 
            Information option:</emphasis> The platform must include the 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> in the OF device tree 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>memory</literal></emphasis> node and the nodes of each processor, memory 
            region, and PCI bridge onto which IOAs may be plugged if the component is 
            dedicated to the partition. (The device tree node for a component that the 
            platform intends to virtualize should include an 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property if the associativity 
            domain information is substantially accurate.)</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
     	
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_90086" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the NUMA option and SPLPAR 
            option:</emphasis> In the case that both the NUMA and SPLPAR options are 
            implemented, Requirement <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_19785"/> is modified 
            to remove processors from the list of system elements that must include the 
            respective properties or interfaces described by that requirement. (The 
            platform is encouraged to provide processor associativity information if it is 
            substantially accurate.)</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>The <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property contains one or more lists of numbers representing the 
    resource&#x2019;s platform grouping domains. Each list, starts with a number 
    representing the domain number of the highest level grouping within which the 
    platform is capable of supporting direct access. This highest level may be a 
    NUMA collective or possibly a cluster of machines with direct DMA access. 
    Successive numbers represent sub-divisions of the previous higher level within 
    which the expected mean value of the performance relative to outside resources 
    is substantially similar. Implementations determine the number of levels that 
    they report, subject to Requirements <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_19785"/> 
    and <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_29131"/>. The lowest level always being 
    that of the allocable resource itself. The user of this information is 
    cautioned not to imply any specific physical/logical significance of the 
    various intermediate levels.</para>
     	
    <variablelist>
     	<varlistentry xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_29131">
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_90086" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the NUMA or Associativity 
            Information option:</emphasis> Differing levels of resource grouping represented in the 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property 
            must reflect statistically repeatable differences in the expected mean of 
            measured performance.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
     	
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_90086" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the NUMA or Associativity 
            Information option:</emphasis> The expected mean performance of any resource 
            of a given type within the same grouping domain represented in the 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property relative to 
            resources outside of that grouping domain must be substantially similar.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>The reason that the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis>
    property may contain 
    multiple associativity lists is that a resource may be multiply connected into 
    the platform. This resource then has a different associativity characteristics 
    relative to its multiple connections. To determine the associativity between 
    any two resources, the OS scans down the two resources associativity lists in 
    all pair wise combinations counting how many domains are the same until the 
    first domain where the two list do not agree. The highest such count is the 
    associativity between the two resources.</para>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="sec_numa_perf_distance">
    <title>Relative Performance Distance</title>
    <para>An OS applies its NUMA tuning techniques based upon associativity and 
    relative performance distance attributes. As a guide to relative performance 
    distance, RISC Platforms provide the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property. The information in this property represents a first order approximation to points 
    having associativity and relative performance distance characteristics deemed 
    to be of significant interest to optimizing client program performance.</para>
    <para>The contents of the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property is dependent upon the setting of the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,architecture-vec-5&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property byte 5 bit 0. The bit value of zero allows the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property string 
    to indicate logical structure points; this form is being deprecated for new 
    implementations in favor of the form indicated by the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,architecture-vec-5&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property byte 5 bit 0 having the value of one in which the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property string 
    represents boundaries between associativity domains presented by the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property containing 
    &#x201C;near&#x201D; and &#x201C;far&#x201D; resources.</para>

    <variablelist>
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_numa_perf_distance" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the NUMA or Associativity 
            Information option:</emphasis> The RTAS OF device tree node must contain the 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis>.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
    <section>
      <title>Form 0</title>
      <para>When the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,architecture-vec-5&#x201D;</literal></emphasis>
      property byte 5 bit 0 has the value of zero, the 
      <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property defines 
      reference points in the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
      property (see <xref linkend="LoPAR.DeviceTree"/>) which roughly correspond to 
      traditional notions of platform topology constructs. It is important for the 
      user to realize that these reference points are not exact and their 
      characteristics vary among implementations. </para>
      <para>The first integer in the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
      property relates the 1 based ordinal in the associativity lists of the platform&#x2019;s 
      <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property associated 
      with the traditional notion of a symmetric multi-processor within a NUMA 
      platform. That is the level that represents building blocks of processors and 
      memory that have the following characteristics:</para>

      <itemizedlist>		      
        <listitem>
          <para>An OS is likely to view all members having roughly uniform access 
          characteristics.</para>
        </listitem>
        
        <listitem>
          <para>Represents the highest level before an OS is likely to notice 
          major Non-Uniformity of access.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>		      

      <para>The second integer in the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
      property relates the 1 based ordinal in the associativity lists of the platform&#x2019;s 
      <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property associated 
      with the traditional notion of a processor group which is sometimes packaged in 
      a multi-chip module. A processor group has similar characteristics to an SMP, 
      however, several processor groups get packaged densely within the same physical 
      enclosure forming an SMP. While the intra processor group accesses are 
      measurably greater than inter processor group accesses they are a second order 
      effect. </para>
      <para>Subsequent <emphasis>ibm,associativity-reference-points</emphasis> entries are reserved.</para>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_82008">
      <title>Form 1</title>
      <para>When the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,architecture-vec-5&#x201D;</literal></emphasis>
      property byte 5 bit 0 has the value of one, the 
      <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property 
      indicates boundaries between associativity domains presented by the 
      <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativity&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property containing 
      &#x201C;near&#x201D; and &#x201C;far&#x201D; resources. The first such boundary 
      in the list represents the 1 based ordinal in the associativity lists of the 
      most significant boundary, with subsequent entries indicating progressively 
      less significant boundaries.</para>
      <para><emphasis role="bold">Note</emphasis>: Platforms are encouraged to report 
      boundaries of actual significance. Thus if a platform has only a single 
      significant boundary to report, the preferred form of the 
      <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,associativ&#xAC;ity-reference-points&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> would 
      contain a single entry. However, providing two or more entries that reference 
      the same associativity domains provides equivalent information and is a legal 
      representation.</para>
    </section>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="sec_numa_dr_cross_cec_io">
    <title>Dynamic Reconfiguration with Cross CEC I/O Drawers</title>
    <para>Should the configuration change in such a way that the associativity 
    between an OS image&#x2019;s resources changes, the platform notifies the OS 
    via an event scan log. See <xref linkend="LoPAR.Error"/>. </para>

    <variablelist>
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_numa_dr_cross_cec_io" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the NUMA or Associativity 
            Information option:</emphasis> If the platform configuration changes in such a 
            way that the associativity between an OS image&#x2019;s resources might have 
            changed, the platform must notify the OS via an event scan or check exception 
            log.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="sec_numa_max_domains">
    <title>Maximum Associativity Domains</title>
    <para>Since the number of associativity domains that a platform may exhibit 
    is not apparent from the associativity properties presented at boot time, the 
    platform provides the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,max-associativity-domains&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> 
    property in the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>/rtas</literal></emphasis> node of the device tree (see 
    <xref linkend="LoPAR.DeviceTree"/>).</para>

    <variablelist>
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="sec_numa_max_domains" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the NUMA or Associativity 
            Information option:</emphasis> The platform must provide the 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>&#x201C;ibm,max-associativity-domains&#x201D;</literal></emphasis> property in 
            the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>/rtas</literal></emphasis> node of the device tree.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
  </section>
  
  <section xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_88496">
    <title>Platform Resource Reassignment Notification Option (PRRN)</title>
    <para>LoPAR platforms that implement the LPAR option are allowed to 
    transparently reassign the platform resources that are used by a partition. For 
    instance, if a processor or memory unit is predicted to fail, the platform may 
    transparently move the processing to an equivalent unused processor or the 
    memory state to an equivalent unused memory unit. However, reassigning 
    resources across NUMA boundaries may alter the performance of the partition. 
    When such reassignment is necessary, the PRRN option provides mechanisms that 
    inform the supporting OS of changes to the affinity among its platform 
    resources. It is expected that handling such notifications will involve 
    significant OS processing, therefore, changing affinity should be avoided, and 
    when it is necessary to change the affinity of several of the resources owned 
    by a partition, a single notification after all such changes have occurred is 
    preferred.</para>
    <para>The OS and platform firmware negotiate their mutual support of the 
    PRRN option via the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,client-architecture-support</literal></emphasis> 
    interface (See <xref linkend="LoPAR.DeviceTree"/>). Should a partition be 
    migrated from a platform that did not support the PRRN option, the target 
    platform does not notify the partition&#x2019;s OS of any PRRN events and, when 
    possible avoids changing the affinity among the partition&#x2019;s resources. 
    Partitions that are about to be migrated complete/abort any in-process affinity 
    change processing prior to the migration, and if the target platform does not 
    support the PRRN option the partition will simply see no more PRRN 
    events.</para>
    <para>A PRRN event is signaled via the RTAS <emphasis>event-scan</emphasis> 
    mechanism, which returns a Hot Plug Event message &#x201C;fixed 
    part&#x201D; (See <xref linkend="LoPAR.Error"/>) indicating &#x201C;Platform 
    Resource Reassignment&#x201D;. In response to the Hot Plug Event message, the 
    OS may call <emphasis>ibm,update-nodes</emphasis> to determine which resources 
    were reassigned, and then <emphasis>ibm,update-properties</emphasis> to obtain 
    the new affinity information about those resources.</para>
    <para>The PRRN <emphasis>event-scan</emphasis> RTAS message contains only 
    the &#x201C;fixed part&#x201D; with the &#x201C;Type&#x201D; field set to the 
    value 160 and no Extended Event Log. The four (4) byte Extended Event Log 
    Length field is repurposed, since no Extended Event Log message is included, to 
    pass the &#x201C;scope&#x201D; parameter that causes the 
    <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,update-nodes</literal></emphasis> to return the nodes affected by the specific 
    resource reassignment.</para>
    <para><emphasis role="bold">Requirements:</emphasis></para>

    <variablelist>
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_88496" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-1.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PRRN Option:</emphasis> 
            The platform must support the negotiation of the Associativity Information 
            Option Control Platform Resource Reassignment Notification (Affinity Change) 
            flag via the <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,client-architecture-support</literal></emphasis> 
            interface.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
     	
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_88496" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-2.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PRRN Option:</emphasis> 
            If the client code did not claim support for the PRRN option via the 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,client-architecture-support</literal></emphasis> interface the platform must not 
            present PRRN events per section <xref 
            linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_88496"/>.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
     	
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_88496" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-3.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the combination of the PRRN 
            and Partition Suspension Options:</emphasis> To avoid firmware function 
            conflicts the client code must complete or abort any PRRN processing prior to 
            exercising the Partition Suspension option.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
     	
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_88496" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-4.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PRRN Option:</emphasis> 
            The platform must inform the client code of platform resource reassignments via 
            the <emphasis>event-scan</emphasis> RTAS mechanism with a &#x201C;fixed 
            part&#x201D; only event return message as presented in <xref 
            linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_37599"/></para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
     	
     	<varlistentry>
        <term><emphasis role="bold">R1-<xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569346_88496" 
        xrefstyle="select: labelnumber nopage"/>-5.</emphasis></term>
          <listitem>
            <para><emphasis role="bold">For the PRRN Option:</emphasis> 
            The platform must support the Platform Resource Reassignment scope (negative of 
            the value contained in bits 32:64 of the RTAS Event Return Format (Fixed Part) 
            for PRRN events) input parameter to input the 
            <emphasis role="bold"><literal>ibm,update-nodes</literal></emphasis> RTAS call.</para>
          </listitem>
     	</varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569346_37599">
      <title>RTAS Event Return Format (Fixed Part) for PRRN events</title>
      <?dbhtml table-width="80%" ?><?dbfo table-width="80%" ?>
      <tgroup cols="2">
        <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="30*" align="center"/>
        <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="70*"/>
        <thead valign="middle">
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Bit Field Name (bitnumber(s))</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
            <entry align="center">
              <para>
                <emphasis role="bold">Description, Values (Described in <xref linkend="LoPAR.RTAS"/>)</emphasis>
              </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        <tbody valign="middle">
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Version (0:7)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> A distinct value used to identify the architectural version of message</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Severity (8:10)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> EVENT (1)</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> RTAS Disposition (11:12)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> FULLY_RECOVERED(0)</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Optional_Part_Presence (13)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> NOT_PRESENT (0): The optional Extended Error Log is not present.</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Reserved (14:15)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> 0b00</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Initiator (16:19)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> HOT PLUG (6) </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Target (20:23)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> UNKNOWN (0): Not Applicable</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Type (24:31)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> Platform Resource Reassignment (160) &#x2013; includes Change Scope in bits 32:63</para>
            </entry>
          </row>
          <row>
            <entry>
              <para> Extended Event Log Length / Change Scope (32:63)</para>
            </entry>
            <entry>
              <para> The scope parameter to be input the <emphasis>ibm,update-nodes</emphasis> RTAS call
              to retrieve the nodes that were changed by selected &#x201C;Hot Plug&#x201D; 
              events. </para>
            </entry>
          </row>
        </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
</chapter>
