<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2016 OpenPOWER Foundation
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  
-->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" 
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" 
         version="5.0" 
         xml:id="section_PAPR_audience">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  
          <title> Audience for This Document</title>
          
          <para>This document defines the platform and system requirements for designing 
          LoPAR platforms. This document is the primary source of information that a platform, 
          OS, or hardware component developer would need to create compatible products. 
          Additional requirements are defined by the industry standards referenced in this 
          document.</para>
          
          <para>This document describes the platform to OS interface which must be provided 
          in these platforms. Platform designers must assemble components and firmware which 
          match this interface. Also, the document defines minimum system configuration 
          requirements. Platform designers must meet or exceed these minimums to build a 
          standard platform. </para>
          
          <para>This document must be used by those designing compatible software including 
          the OS, boot software, or firmware. If a function is supported, software developers 
          must provide support for the interfaces described in this document. This software 
          must provide the mandatory functions and capabilities as described in the requirements 
          in this document. However, this document does not limit this software from going beyond 
          the specification through software tailored to specific hardware. For example, the OS 
          must implement the interface to the required abstracted interfaces to hardware, but the 
          OS may also implement fast paths to specific hardware that it recognizes.</para>
          
</section>
