<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright (c) 2016 OpenPOWER Foundation
  
  Licensed under the Apache License, Version 2.0 (the "License");
  you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
  You may obtain a copy of the License at

    http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0

  Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
  distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS,
  WITHOUT WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied.
  See the License for the specific language governing permissions and
  limitations under the License.
  
-->
<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0" xml:id="section_PAPR_conventions">
  <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
  
          <title> Document-specific Conventions</title>
            
          <simplesect>
            <title> Requirement Enumeration</title>
            <para>Within the body of this document requirements are clearly defined by separate 
            paragraphs beginning with a bold text sequence number. A list of all these are 
            available as a separate document. These requirements may point to other standards 
            documents, or figures or tables which conveniently show the requirement. The 
            referenced material becomes part of the requirements in this document. Users of this 
            document must comply with these requirements to build a standard platform. Other 
            material in this document is supportive description of these requirements, architecture 
            notes, or implementation notes. Architecture or implementation notes are flagged with 
            a descriptive phrase&#8212;for example, &#8220;Hardware Implementation Note&#8221;&#8212; 
            and followed by indented paragraphs. The descriptive material and notes provide no 
            additional requirements and may be used for their information content.</para>
          </simplesect>
          
          <simplesect>
            <title> Big-Endian Numbering</title>
            <para>Big-Endian numbering of bytes and bits is used in this document, unless 
            indicated otherwise. Numbering of bits starts at 0 for the most significant bit and 
            continues to the least significant bit, unless indicated otherwise. All data structures 
            used for communicating between the OS and the platform (for example, RTAS and hypervisor 
            calls) will be in Big-Endian format, unless otherwise designated.</para>
          </simplesect>
          
          <simplesect>
            <title> Hypertext Links</title>
            <para>This document makes use of hypertext links. Cross references, Table of Contents 
            entries, List of Tables entries, and List of Figures entries are all clickable hypertext 
            links, to make navigation of the document easier.</para>
          </simplesect>
          
          <simplesect>
            <title> Specific Terms</title>
            <para>In this document:</para>
            <itemizedlist>
	          <listitem>
                <para>The term &#8220;Processor Architecture&#8221; (PA) is used to mean compliance with 
                the requirements specified in <citetitle><xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569387_99718"/></citetitle>.</para>
	          </listitem>
	          <listitem>
               <para>The term &#8220;processor&#8221; is used as a general term to mean &#8220;processor,
                &#8221; or &#8220;processor core,&#8221; or &#8220;thread of a multi-threaded processor 
                design.&#8221; In any case where it makes a difference, the specific terminology for that 
                case is used.</para>
	          </listitem>
	          <listitem>
                <para>The term &#8220;real&#8221; used in relationship with addresses is a generic term 
                that means &#8220;processor real address&#8221; when the platform is running in SMP (non-LPAR) 
                mode and partition &#8220;logical real address&#8221; when the platform is running in LPAR 
                mode.</para>
	          </listitem>
	          <listitem>
                <para>The term &#8220;PCI&#8221; is used as a general term to describe the most recent 
                versions of all forms of PCI standards. In cases where there are significant differences 
                between individual PCI standards, the following terminology is used to differentiate between 
                the PCI standards: conventional PCI, PCI-X, and PCI Express.</para>
	          </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </simplesect>
          
          <simplesect>
            <title> Typographical Conventions</title>
            <para>Typographical conventions used in this document are described in 
            <xref linkend="dbdoclet.50569325_36717"/>.</para>
            <para><anchor xml:id="dbdoclet.50569325_12795" xreflabel=""/>&#160;</para>
            <table frame="all" pgwide="1" xml:id="dbdoclet.50569325_36717">
              <title> Typographical Conventions </title>
              <tgroup cols="2">
                <colspec colname="c1" colwidth="40*"/>
                <colspec colname="c2" colwidth="60*"/>
                <thead><row>
                    <entry><para><emphasis role="bold">Text Element</emphasis></para></entry>
                    <entry><para><emphasis role="bold">Description of Use</emphasis></para></entry>
                  </row>
                  </thead><tbody>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> Rn-m-x.</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> A requirement number. The number &#8220;n&#8221; indicates a requirement 
                    sequence number and is changed only when it is necessary change the sequence numbers 
                    of one or more requirements on an update. The number &#8220;m&#8221; is the section 
                    that the requirement appears in, and the number &#8220;x&#8221; is the number of the 
                    requirement within that section. The sequence numbers are automatically generated and 
                    are restarted at the beginning of each new section. Sequence numbers for existing 
                    requirements will not change unless it becomes necessary to insert a requirement between 
                    other requirements or to add a section that renumbers other sections (at which point, 
                    the number &#8220;n&#8221; will be incremented for the next publication of the document).</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis> Italics</emphasis></para></entry>
                    <entry><para> Used for emphasis such as the first time a new term is used. </para>
                    <para>Indicates a book title. </para><para>Indicates PA instruction mnemonics. </para>
                    <para>Indicates RTAS function, field names, and parameter names</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> <emphasis role="bold"><literal> Courier Bold</literal></emphasis></para></entry>
                    <entry><para> Indicates OF properties, methods, configuration variables, node names 
                    and encode functions (for example, <emphasis> encode-int</emphasis> and <emphasis> 
                    encode-string</emphasis> ). In addition, OF properties are enclosed in quotes.</para>
                    <para>Indicates NVRAM partition names</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> <literal>&#8220;Courier&#8221;</literal> (not bold, enclosed in quotes)</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> Indicates a character string value.</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> 0xnnnn</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> Prefix to denote hexadecimal numbers. </para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> 0bnnnn</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> Prefix to denote binary numbers. </para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> nnnnn</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> Numbers without a prefix are decimal numbers. </para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> 0xF... FFF100</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> This hexadecimal notation represents a replication of the hexadecimal 
                    character to the right of the ellipsis to fill out the field width. For example, the 
                    address 0xF... FFF100 would be 0xFFFFF100 on a processor with a 32-bit address bus or 
                    0xFFFFFFFFFFFFF100 on a processor with a 64-bit address bus.</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> 0:9</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> Ranges of bits are specified by two numbers separated by a colon. The 
                    range includes the first number, all numbers in between, and the last number.</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> 0xm-0xn</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> A range of addresses or values within the document is always inclusive, 
                    from m up to and including n.</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> &lt;token&gt;</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> This notation means the character or character string named within the 
                    less than and greater than symbols is used in the place of the symbols and name. For 
                    instance, the property name <emphasis role="bold"> &#8220;ibm,sensor-</emphasis> <emphasis>&lt;token&gt;</emphasis>
                    <emphasis role="bold">&#8221;</emphasis> indicates the set of properties 
                    <emphasis role="bold">&#8220;ibm,sensor-9000&#8221;</emphasis>,
                    <emphasis role="bold">&#8220;ibm,sensor-9001&#8221;</emphasis> , . . .</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> Reserved For Compatibility</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> This notation is a placeholder used to reserve numbering (for example, 
                    chapter, section and requirement numbers) so that subsequent numbering remains consistent 
                    with document changes.</para></entry>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                    <entry><para> NULL vs. null</para></entry>
                    <entry><para> NULL designates an ASCII NULL string (0x00). The term &#8220;null&#8221; 
                    indicates the empty set.</para></entry>
                  </row>
                </tbody>
              </tgroup>
            </table>
          </simplesect>
          
</section>
